欢迎来到栖目See Movie私人影院
《此时》读者见面会 作者：杰西·华莱士
你认为这本书算自传式的吗？
这个...
Well, I mean...
...什么书不是自传式的呢？
...isn't everything autobiographical?
我们都是通过自己那小小的钥匙孔 看外面的世界，对吧？
I mean, we all see the world through our own tiny keyhole, right?
我是说，我总想起汤玛斯·沃尔夫说的
I mean, I always think of Thomas Wolfe.
你看过“天使望故乡”那本书 前面那短短一页的“致读者”吗？
Have you ever seen that little one-page "Note to Reader"...
你知道我在说什么吧？
...in the front of Look Homeward, Angel?
总之，他说我们的生命就是 由点点滴滴集合而成的
Anyway, he says that we are the sum of all the moments of our lives...
...而任何人坐下来，写出来的 都不过是自己生命中的体验...
...and anybody who sits down to write will use the clay of their own life...
...谁都无法回避
...that you can't avoid that.
所以当我审视我的人生， 我必须得承认，我发现...
So when I look at my own life, I have to admit, right, that I...
我从来没有经历过枪林弹雨 或是暴力事件，起码没真正体验过
I've never been around a bunch of guns or violence, you know, not really.
没有什么政治阴谋， 也没什么直升机失事
No political intrigue or a helicopter crash, right?
但是我的人生，从我个人观点来看 仍然是富有戏剧性的
But my life, from my own point of view, has been full of drama, right?
于是我想也许我也能写本书...
And so I thought, if I could write a book...
...记录下我见到某人时的感觉
...that could capture what it's like to really meet somebody...
我是说，我经历过的最刺激的事情之一
One of the most exciting things that's happened to me...
...就是真正和某人见面， 让两个人心灵相通
...is to meet somebody, make that connection.
而如果我能把它表现出来 你明白吗，抓住那一刻的感觉...
And if I could make that valuable, you know, to capture that...
...那就是我的写作意图了，亦或者....
...that would be the attempt, or...
你满意我的回答吗？
Did I answer your question?
我干脆就直说吧...
I'll try to be more specific.
我在火车上遇见一个年轻的法国女郎
Was there ever a French young woman on a train you met...
并和她共度良宵
...and spent an evening with?
这个，对我来说...我是说...
See, to me, that... I mean...
- ...这并不重要，你懂吗？ - 就是说的确有了？
...that's not important, you know? - So that's a yes?
好吧，既然我人在法国，这又是 我签名售书的最后一站，那就算有吧
All right, since I'm in France and this is the last stop of my book tour, yes.
谢谢
Thank you.
华莱士先生，这本书的结尾给我们留下了悬念
Mr. Wallace, the book ends on an ambiguous note.
我们不知道
We don't know.
你认为他们六个月之后会重聚吗？
Do you think they get back together in six months...
就像他们彼此承诺的那样？
...like they promise each other?
像他们保证的？
Like they promised?
我认为这个问题实际上是，是个....
I think how you answer that, you know, is...
是个很好的测试，看看你到底是 喜欢浪漫还是对它嗤之以鼻
It's a good test, right, if you're a romantic or a cynic.
我是说，你认为他们会重聚的，对吧？
Right? I mean, you think they get back together, right?
- 显然你并不这么认为 - 是的
- You don't, for sure. - No.
还是你希望他们会 不过你无法肯定
And you hope they do, but you're not sure.
- 所以你才问这个问题 - 你认为他们会重聚吗？
- That's why you're asking the question. - Do you think they get back together?
我是说你们重聚了吗？ 在现实生活中？
I mean, did you in real life?
现实生活中...？
Did I in real...?
要用我祖父的话来说啊
Look, in the words of my grandfather, okay:
天晓得会不会
"To answer that would take the piss out of the whole thing. "
我们的时间只够问最后一个问题了
We just have the time for one last question.
你下一本书将是什么？
What is your next book?
我不知道，老兄，我真的不知道...
I don't know, man. I don't know.
我一直...一直在考虑这个构思...
I've been... I've been thinking about this...
我总是想写本书...
Well, I always kind of wanted to write a book...
...一切都发生在一首流行歌曲那么长时间内
...that all took place within the space of a pop song.
总共大概3到4分钟吧
Like three or four minutes long, the whole thing.
整个故事大概是说有个男人...
The story, the idea, is that there's this guy, right...
...他非常的沮丧，因为...
...and he's totally depressed.
他最大的梦想就是拥有一段 轰轰烈烈的爱情，一次冒险...
His great dream was to be a lover, an adventurer, you know...
...比如开着摩托周游南美
...riding motorcycles through South America.
但是事实上他只是坐在大理石桌前吃着龙虾
And instead he's sitting at a marble table eating lobster.
他有份不错的工作，妻子也很漂亮
He's got a good job and a beautiful wife, right, but that...
他应有尽有，但是这并不是他真正想要的...
Everything that he needs. But that doesn't matter...
...因为他真正想要的是为某种理想而战
...because what he wants is to fight for meaning.
你明白吗，快乐来自于过程
You know? Happiness is in the doing, right?
而不是因为你得到了你想要的东西
Not in the getting what you want.
总之，他坐在那里，突然间...
So he's sitting there, and just that second...
...他五岁的小女儿跳上了桌子
...his little 5-year-old daughter hops up on the table.
他知道她该下来，因为她可能会受伤
And he knows that she should get down, because she could get hurt.
但是她正穿着夏日的裙子 随着那首歌翩翩起舞
But she's dancing to this pop song in a summer dress.
然后一晃眼
And he looks down...
...突然间，他回到了十六岁
...and all of a sudden, he's 6.
他的高中女友正送他回家
And his high-school sweetheart is dropping him off at home.
而他们刚刚度过了他们的初夜 她很爱他...
And they just lost their virginity, and she loves him...
...而汽车收音机里里播放着的 是同样的一首曲子
...and the same song is playing on the car radio.
然后她爬上了车顶，开始在那里跳舞
And she climbs up and starts dancing on the roof of the car.
这一下，他开始很担心她！
And now he's worried about her.
她很美，表情也竟然和她女儿一模一样
And she's beautiful, with a facial expression just like his daughter's.
事实上，这可能就是 他为什么会喜欢她的原因
In fact, maybe that's why he even likes her.
你懂吗，他知道他并不是身处回忆之中...
You see, he knows he's not remembering this dance...
...而是他就在那里，他同时 出现在人生的两个场景之中
...he's there. He's there, in both moments, simultaneously.
就在这一瞬间，他全部的人生 好像都交汇到了一起
And just for an instant, all his life is just folding in on itself.
对他来说，时间明显是个谎言
And it's obvious to him that time is a lie.
因为那一刻将一直延伸下去...
That it's all happening all the time...
..而且.每个时刻之内都包含着另一个时刻...
...and inside every moment is another moment...
...一切的一切，都发生在同一瞬间
...all happening simultaneously.
总之，这就是我大概的想法，总之
Anyway, that's kind of the idea. Anyway.
我们的作者很快就得去机场了...
Our author has to be going to the airport soon...
...那么，谢谢各位今天下午光临
...so thank you all very much for coming over this afternoon.
尤其要感谢华莱士先生和我们 共度了这么美好的一个下午
And a special thanks to Mr. Wallace for being with us.
谢谢，谢谢
Thank you. Thank you.
希望你出下本书的时候 我们还能在这见到你！
We hope to see you here again with your next book.
（法语）感谢大家光临
（法语）我们为大家准备了香槟和一些小点心
（法语）请尽情享受吧
Thank you all. How much longer before I have to go to the airport?
谢谢各位，我必须在几点之前去机场？
哦，你必须在七点半之前离开？
Oh, you should leave at 7:30...
- 最迟七点半！ - 好
- Seven-thirty at the very latest. - Okay.
- 嗨 - 你好
- Hi. - Hello.
- 你还好吗？ - 很好，你呢？
- How are you? - Good, and you?
挺好，是的，我很好，我...
I'm good, yeah, I'm great. I'm...
你愿意...我是说...去喝杯咖啡什么的吗？
Do you wanna, maybe, get a cup of coffee?
他不是说你要赶飞机吗？
Didn't he just say you have a plane to catch?
是啊...不过时间还早
Yeah. But, I mean, I have a little time.
- 那好吧 - 好吗？好，那，让我....
- Okay. - Yeah? All right, well, let me...
我在外面等你
I'll meet you outside. Okay.
我出去一下，喝杯咖啡
Excuse me. I'm just gonna go get a cup of coffee.
- 我七点一刻回来 - 这些书你都签了名吗？
- I'll be back at 7: 5. - Did you sign all these?
- 是的，我肯定签了 - 拿着你的司机菲利普的名片...
- Yeah, I sure did. - Get your driver Philippe's card...
...这样你要是晚了，就用手机给他打电话
...so you can call his cell if you're running late.
我们会把你的包放在车里 这样你就不会晚了
We'll put your bags in the car so you're not late.
- 好的，谢谢你 - （法语）非常感谢
- All right, thanks for everything. - Thank you.
谁是菲利普？
Which one's Philippe?
（法语）菲利普，把你的名片给他， 上面有你的手机号码
（法语）谢谢
- 真难以置信你会在这里 - 我就住在巴黎
- I can't believe you're here. - I live here in Paris.
你真的不用多呆几天吗？ 你不用再和谁谈什么了吗？
Are you sure you don't have to stay? You're not supposed to talk more?
不，他们都开始烦我了 我昨晚整夜都在这里
They're sick of me. I spent the night here.
- 哦，真的吗？ - 是啊，他们楼上有间阁楼
- You did? - Yeah, they got a loft upstairs.
- 你怎么样？这感觉真奇怪 - 我很好
- How are you? This is so weird. - I'm fine.
- 见到你真高兴！ - 见到你真高兴！
- It's good to see you. - It's good to see you.
- 那你想去喝杯咖啡吗？ - 哦，当然
- So you want to go to a caf? - Yeah.
那好，那边不远有一家很不错
Okay. There's one a little further that I like.
我刚才见到你的时候我都快傻了
I thought I was gonna totally lose it in there when I first saw you.
你怎么会知道我会来这的呢？
How did you know I was gonna be here?
这是我在巴黎最喜欢的书店了 你可以坐在那里看一天书
It's my favorite bookstore in Paris. You can sit down for hours and read.
我很喜欢这样，那儿是有跳蚤，不过，你知道的....
I love it. There's fleas, but, you know...
我知道，我简直感觉昨晚有只猫睡在我头上
I know. I think a cat slept on my head last night.
我一个月前就书店日历上看到你的照片
I saw your picture on the calendar about a month ago...
知道你会来这里
...and that you were going to be here.
有意思的是，我读了你的书，一小段而已
It's funny, because I read an article on your book...
- 我有种朦朦胧胧的的亲切感 - 朦朦胧胧？是吗？
...and it sounded vaguely familiar. - Vaguely? Yeah.
是的，只不过是在见到你的照片 之后才有的，所以...
But I didn't put it all together until I saw your photo. So...
你看过那书了吗？
Did you have a chance to read it?
是的，我....
Yes, I...
你的书让我感到惊喜，你应该体会得到的
I was really, really surprised, as you can imagine.
我是说，我对它爱不释手
I mean, I had to read it twice, actually.
- 是吗？ - 是的
- Yeah? - Yeah.
（法语）写得马马虎虎？
No, I liked it. It's very romantic.
不，我很喜欢，非常浪漫！
我平时不爱看类似的书 但是你写的真好
I usually don't like that, but it's really well-written.
- 写的非常好，祝贺你！ - 好吧，谢谢
- It's well-written. Congratulations. - All right. Thank you.
- 等等 - 怎么啦？
- Wait. - What?
在我们出发前，我得问你...
Before we go anywhere, I have to ask you...
没问题，什么事？
Sure. What?
那年十二月，你去维也纳了吗？
Did you show up in Vienna that December?
- 呃，你去了吗？ - 没有，我没能去成，但是...你去了吗？
- Did you? - No, I couldn't. But did you?
- 我必须要知道，这对我很重要！ - 为什么，既然你都没去？
- I need to know. It's important to me. - Why, if you didn't?
那，你去了吗？
Well, did you?
没有
No.
哦，谢天谢地你没去！
Thank God you didn't.
- 哦，天啊 - 谢天谢地你没去
- Oh, my God. - Thank God you didn't.
我是说，幸亏我没去，你也没去 要是我们两个只有一个人去了...
Thank God I didn't and you didn't. If one of us had showed up alone...
- ...那简直是糟透了 - 我知道，我知道，我一直担心这个
...that would have sucked. - I was so concerned.
我一直因为没去而内疚，但是我确实没法！ 我祖母那之前几天过世了
I felt horrible about not being there, but I couldn't. My grandma died...
那天是她下葬的日子，十二月十六日
...and she was buried that day, December 6th.
- 她过世了？就是布达佩斯的那一位？ - 是的，你还记得？
- The one in Budapest? - Yes. You remember that?
- 当然，我什么都记得 - 噢，对了，你书中还提到了
- I remember everything. - Of course, it was in your book.
总之，我的确想过去维也纳的
But anyway, I was about to fly to Vienna, you know...
但是噩耗突然传来，我只能去参加葬礼了
...and we heard the news about her, and of course I had to go to the funeral.
是啊，听到这个真让人难过
Yeah, I'm sorry to hear that.
我知道，反正你也没去...
I know. But you weren't there anyway.
等等，你为什么没去？
Wait. Why weren't you there?
我要是能去的话一定会去的 我定了计划，而且我...
I would have been there if I could have. I made plans...
你最好能找到个好一点的理由！
You better have a good reason.
怎么了？
What?
哦，不！
Oh, no.
你去那了，是吗？
No, you were there, weren't you?
哦，不，真糟糕！
Oh, no, that's terrible!
我知道，我笑了，不过我不是有意的！
I'm laughing, but I don't mean it.
你当时生我气了吧，一定是的
Did you hate me? You must've hated me.
- 你一直都在生我的气吧？一定是的 - 没有
- Have you been hating me all this time? - No.
- 有，你生我气了 - 没有
- Yes, you have. - No.
但你现在不生气了，对吧？
But you can't hate me now, right?
- 我是说，我祖母... - 我没生你的气，又不是什么大事
- I mean, my grandma... - I don't hate you. It's no big deal.
我大老远飞过去，你却放我的鸽子
I flew all the way over there, you blew the thing off.
于是我的人生自此一蹶不振 不过，这又算什么呢
My life's been a big nosedive since, but it's not a problem.
- 我只是开玩笑，开玩笑 - 别这么说，我真无法相信
- No, I'm kidding. - Don't say that. I can't believe it.
我一定是把你气疯了，我真抱歉
You must have been so angry with me. I'm so sorry.
我真的很想去的，没什么比这个更重要了！
I wanted to be there, more than anything in the world.
- 不开玩笑了，我发誓... - 你不能生气啊，我祖母...
- Honestly, I swear... - You can't be angry, my grandmother...
我懂，我真的想到了， 你大概就是被这种事情缠住了
I know. I honestly thought that something like that might have happened.
我确实是非常失望，不过...
I was definitely bummed, but...
我感到最遗憾的还是因为我们没有 交换电话号码，或者任何其他个人信息
Mostly I was mad we hadn't exchanged any phone numbers or any information.
瞧瞧我们干的傻事，没法彼此联系
That was so stupid. No way to get in touch.
- 对啊，没法继续下去了 - 我甚至不知道你姓什么
- Nothing to go on. - I didn't know your last name.
记得吗，我们都担心如果我们开始通信，打电话...
Remember, we were both afraid if we started writing and calling...
- ...感觉会不会慢慢的就变淡了 - 是啊，而且肯定不会慢慢变淡
...that it would slowly fade out. - It definitely wasn't a slow fade.
肯定不会
No, it sure wasn't.
我们都怀念曾经拥有的感觉
We wanted to pick up where we left off.
如果这份感觉可以永存的话 那就再好不过了
Which would have been fine if it had worked. Oh, well.
那么....
So...
- 你在维也纳待了多久？ - 就几天
- How long were you in Vienna, then? - Just a couple days.
你碰到其他女孩了吗？
Did you meet another girl?
啊，是啊，她叫格蕾岑，她棒极了
Yeah, her name was Gretchen and she was amazing.
- 真的？ - 是啊，事实上，那书是写你们两个的
The book's really a composite of the two of you.
真的吗？
No, I'm kidding. You wouldn't believe... I even went back to the train station.
没这回事，我只是开玩笑！ 你不会相信的，我甚至还回到火车站过
我支了个牌子，写了我旅馆的电话号码， 以免你来晚了找不到
I put up signs of my number in the hotel in case you'd been delayed.
- 我真是个笨蛋 - 我们这边走，有人打电话给你吗？
- I was a total dork. - Let's go this way. Did you get any calls?
有几个妓女，拉皮条的
Just a couple hookers looking for a gig.
哦，那真是糟，我是说，你指望让我说什么呢
No, it was awful, I mean, what do you want me to say?
哦，太让人伤心了，我真抱歉！
It's so sad. I'm so sorry.
我就那么转悠了几天，最后，就飞回去了
I walked around for a couple days. Eventually, I flew home.
还欠了我爸2000块
I owed my dad 2000 bucks...
他可是警告我不要碰法国鸡
...who had warned me about French chicks.
他怎么对你形容法国女人的？
What did he tell you about French women?
没什么，他，他从来没有遇见过法国女人
Nothing. He's never met any French women.
他从来没有去过比密西西比河更东的地方
He's never been east of the Mississippi.
那你干嘛不加上一句，“六个月过去了， 那个法国婊子还是没出现”
Why didn't you put, "Six months later, the French bitch didn't show up"?
不，可是我差点这么做了
No, but I did, I did.
- 你真的想过？ - 是的，我是说，我让它看起来更有悬念
- You did? - Yeah. No. I made it more hopeful.
我写了一段虚构的情节，说你最后出现了
I wrote this fictional version where you do show up.
- 哦，你怎么写的？ - 呃...
- Oh, what happens? - Well...
怎么了？
What?
呃，我们整整做了十天爱，这还没完
We make love for about 0 days straight, that's one part of it.
- 哦，真有意思，一个法国荡妇... - 没错
- Interesting. So the French slut, right? - Yeah, exactly.
从那以后，他们开始了解对方
It's just then they get to know each other better...
然后他们意识到彼此并不合适
...and realize they don't get along at all.
- 我喜欢这样，看起来更真实 - 我的编辑可不这么想
- I like that. It's more real. - My editor didn't think that way.
谁都想相信爱情，为了畅销嘛，对吧？
Everyone wants to believe in love. It sells.
是啊，就是如此，所以...
Yeah, exactly, so...
就是说你一切都好，对吧？
So things are going well for you, right? I mean...
- 我是说，你的书是美国畅销书... - 只是本小小的畅销书
- Your book is a bestseller in the U. S. - It's a tiny bestseller.
- 哦，别谦虚啦... - 好吧，没错，理论上说，是的
- Oh, come on. - All right. Officially, yes.
可大多数人连莫比·迪克的书都没读过 又怎么会来读我的？
Most people haven't read Moby Dick. Why should they read my book?
我也没读过莫比·迪克的书 可是我就喜欢你的书，所以...
I haven't read Moby Dick and I liked your book.
- 谢谢 - 即使...
- Thanks. - Even though...
我觉得你把那一晚描绘得太完美了
...I thought you idealized the night of it.
嘿，我说，这可是小说
Come on, it's fiction, right?
- 我本来就得... - 我知道，我知道
- I'm supposed to... - I know, I know.
你知道，有些时候，你让我看起来...
I know. I thought there were times where you made me...
呃，我是说她， 不，还是我...算啦，管她是谁
Well, I mean, her, right? No, me. Okay, whatever.
- 总之有点神经质！ - 你确实有点啊，不是吗？
- A little bit neurotic. - You are a bit like that, aren't you?
- 你认为我神经质？ - 没有，这是个玩笑而已！
- You think I'm neurotic? - No, no, no. Come on, I'm kidding.
我哪那么写了，我才没有呢
Where did I do that? I didn't do that.
我这人就是这样的，你知道的...
Oh, maybe it's just me, you know...
读到一个故事，知道故事是根据自己来写的
Reading something, knowing the character is based on you...
这既让人受宠若惊，也让人心神不宁
...it's both flattering and disturbing at the same time.
怎么会让人心神不宁的？
How is it disturbing?
我不知道，只是... 成为他人记忆中的一部分
I don't know. Just being part of someone else's memory.
透过你的眼看到我自己
Seeing myself through your eyes.
你写了多久？
How long did it take you to write it?
呃，三四年吧，时断时续的
Three or four years, on and off.
哇，你花了那么长时间就为了写 一个晚上发生的事情？
Wow, that's a really long time to be writing about one night.
是啊，我知道，你说的没错
Yeah, I know. Tell me about it.
我总是认为你已经忘记我了
I always assumed you had forgotten me.
没有，我心目中你的印象非常清晰
No, I had a pretty clear picture of you in my mind.
- 我得告诉你件事情，我... - 怎么了？
- I have to tell you something. I just... - What?
这么久以来，我一直想和你聊天 你知道吗，而现在...
I've wanted to talk to you for so long that now... It's just surreal, you know?
- 是啊，我也是 - 现在梦想成真了
I feel like everything should be...
我却觉得不知道该说什么了
我懂，我懂，我们还有多长时间？ 20分钟又30秒？
How long do we have? Twenty minutes and 30 seconds?
不，我们有的是时间 我想多和你聊聊
We got more than that. I wanna know about you.
告诉我你在做什么？
Tell me, what are you doing? What are you up to?
呃，从哪开始呢... 我为绿十字会工作，那是个环保组织
Where to start? I work for Green Cross. It's an environmental organization.
他们是干嘛的？
What are they all about?
这个嘛，基本上来说，我们会关注一些环境问题
We basically work on different environment issues...
比如净化水质，或者销毁化学武器什么的
...from clean water to disarmament of chemical weapons.
你懂吗，涉及环境的国际法什么的
International laws that deal with the environment.
- 那，你为他们做什么？ - 我们走这边
- What do you do for them? - We're going this way.
很多事了
Different things.
比如去年，我在印度待了一阵 在一间水处理工厂工作
Like, last year I was in India for a while, working on a water-treatment plant.
那里的棉纺工业是主要的污染源，所以...
Well, the cotton industry there is a major source of pollution, so...
我是说，听起来你的确做了一些有意义的事情
I mean, it sounds like you're actually doing something.
大多数人，也包括我，只是... 你知道吗，无所事事
Most people, myself included, just sit around and bitch.
美国消耗了世界上大多数资源， 箱式轿车尤其如此
You know, how America's consuming all the world's resources, SUVs suck...
全球也在变暖...
...global warming is real...
很高兴你不是那种狂妄自大的美国人
I'm relieved to hear you're not one of those "freedom fries" Americans.
不过，你是怎么会去做这个的呢？
Hey, you know... But how'd you get into that?
啊，我政治系毕了业 那时我希望为政府工作
I came out of political science, hoping to work for the government.
- 而我确实也替他们干了一阵，哎，太糟了！ - 不好吗？
- And I did for a little while. Terrible. - Not good?
是的，不好，我们这边走 总之，我烦透了...
Yeah, no. Anyway, I got really tired... Let's go this way.
... 与朋友无休止的讨论...
Having this endless conversation with friends...
关于世界怎么会分裂成这样的问题
...about how the world was falling to pieces.
所以我意识到我真正想要做的
So I decided what I really wanted to do was...
就是找到一些可以做好的事情， 然后努力做好它们
...to find things that could be fixed and try to fix them, you know?
我一直觉得你会做这种超酷的事情的
You know, I always thought you'd be doing something cool like that. I did.
谢谢！不过我真的很幸运， 能找到份自己喜欢的工作
Thanks. I just feel really, really lucky to be doing a job I like, you know?
是啊
Yeah.
你知道吗，事实上我曾经非常彷徨 一会儿认为这个世界已经没救了...
I actually alternate in between thinking everything is irrevocably screwed up...
一会儿又认为很多时候还是有转机的
...and things might be getting better in ways.
转机？为什么要这么悲观呢？
Better? How could you possibly say that?
这个嘛，我只是说，你明白吗，比如...
Well, I just mean, you know, like...
我知道这听起来很奇怪， 不过有些事情还是要从好的方面来看
I know it sounds weird, but there are things to be optimistic about.
好啦，我知道你的书畅销 这非常好，我为你感到高兴，不过...
Okay... I know your book is selling, which is great, I'm very happy for you.
让我告诉你真实的世界，好吗？ 世界现在是一团糟！
But let me break the news to you: The world is a mess right now.
从西方世界的观点来看来说，世界的确在变好
From a Western view, things are getting a bit better.
我们正把工业重心转移到发展中国家 那里我们能获得便宜的劳动力...
We're moving industry to developing nations where we can get cheap labor...
...而不去管任何环保法律 军火工业蓬勃发展
...free of any environmental laws. The weapon industry is booming.
每年有五百万人因为水质污染而死去 而这些本来是可以避免的
Five million people die a year from preventable water disease.
告诉我，这样的世界还不够糟糕马？ 我没有生气，我没有生气
How is the world getting better? I'm not angry, I'm not angry.
不过，说吧，我想知道，我很有兴趣！
But come on, I want to know. I'm interested.
好吧，我知道世界上有很多严重的问题
I realize that there are a lot of serious problems in the world.
- 太好了，谢谢你！ - 我的意思是说
- Okay. Thank you. - I mean, I don't even have...
- 我在亚洲根本找不到出版商出我的书 - 好啦
...one publisher in the Asian market. - Okay. All right.
- 说“住嘴”！ - 怎么啦？住嘴
- Say stop. - What? Stop.
听我说，我想说的只是更多的人 意识到这一点了，人们正在反击！
Look, all I'm saying is there's more awareness. People are gonna fight back.
世界还是有可能变得更好的， 因为更多像你这样的人...
The world might be getting better because people like you...
...学会了说出自己的想法
...are educated and speaking out.
最起码的，那些环保问题
Even the very notion of conservation, environmental issues...
最近才出现在词典里
...weren't in the vocabulary till fairly recently.
而现在他们已经成了规范了， 而最后他们都可能被实现
And they're becoming the norm and eventually might be what's expected.
我同意你的看法 但是同时，这也很危险！
I agree with what you're saying, but at the same time it's dangerous.
帝国主义国家会用你这种观点...
An imperialist country can use that kind of thinking...
...来为他们经济上的巧取豪夺找到依据
...to justify their economic greed.
你是在针对某一个帝国主义国家吧，法国佬？
Is there any particular imperialist country you have in mind, there, Frenchie?
- 没，没有 - 没有吗？
- No, not really. - No?
-（法语）晚上好 -（法语）晚上好
- 你愿意坐那边吗？ - 当然，这真不错
- So you wanna sit over there? - Yeah, this is perfect.
哦，哇，可能我想说的只是...
Oh, wow. Maybe what I'm saying is...
...世界的命运就像一个人的命运一样
...the world might be evolving the way a person evolves.
我是说，比如我，我在退步了吗？
Like, I mean, me, for example. Am I getting worse?
我在进步吗？我也不知道！ 当我更年轻的时候，我也更健康...
Am I improving? I don't know. When I was younger, I was healthier...
...但是我充满了危机感，你懂吗？
...but I was wracked with insecurity, you know?
现在，我变老了，遇到的问题也更复杂了
Now I'm older and my problems are deeper...
但是我也更知道怎么来处理它们了
...but I'm more equipped to handle them.
那么，你碰到什么问题了 ？
So, what are your problems?
现在？没事 我没事，我只是...
Right now I don't have any. I don't, you know? I'm just...
...我真他妈高兴能在这！
...damn happy to be here.
我也一样
Me too.
那，你在巴黎待了多久了？
So how long have you been in Paris?
我昨晚才来 12天之内我跑了10个城市
I got in last night. I've done 0 cities in 2 days.
我累极了，所以我很高兴一切都结束了
I'm wrecked. I'm so glad it's over, you know?
我已经厌倦了这种推销
I'm tired of being a huckster.
- 嗨 - 你好
- Hi. - Hello.
（法语）请问您想要点什么？
What do you want?
你要点什么？
A cup of coffee.
一杯咖啡...
（法语）请给我来一杯咖啡和一片柠檬
天，我爱死这家咖啡馆了， 我真希望美国也有这样的地方
God, I love this caf? I wish they had places like this in the U. S.
是啊，当我住那边的时候， 我可想念咖啡馆了
Yeah, I missed caf閟 when I was living over there.
我是说，我是找到了一些我喜欢的地方， 但是那...
I mean, I find a few places I really liked, but there was...
- 你...你在美国呆过？ - 是的，从...96年到99年
- You were living in the U. S.? - Yes, from '96 to '99.
我那时在纽约州立大学上学
I was studying at NYU.
哦，天啊，真难以相信，塞琳！
Oh, God, don't tell me that, Celine.
- 怎么了？ - 没什么，只是...
- What? - No, it's just...
- 没什么， 我是说我... - 怎么了
- Nothing, I mean, I... - What?
我从98年起就住在纽约了 你懂吗，我们那时都在那里！
I've been living in New York since '98. We were there at the same time.
- 纽约？ - 是的
- In New York? - Yeah.
奇怪的是，事实上有几次 我想到过可能会遇见你，
That's weird. It actually crossed my mind a few times that I might run into you...
...但是几率太低了，对吧？而且...
...but the odds are so slim, right? So...
我那时都不知道你住哪个城市
I didn't even know what city you were in.
- 你不是住德克萨斯吗？ - 是的，没错，正是如此，我只是...
- Weren't you somewhere in Texas? - Yeah, yeah, definitely. I just...
我在那住了很久，我只是... 你明白吗，到纽约换换环境
I was for a long time. I just, you know, wanted to try New York.
那你为什么回来了呢？
What brought you back here?
一是我读完了硕士
I had finished my master's, for one...
再来，我的签证到期了
...and no visa, no more visa.
而且，不算这些，我也开始有点妄想狂了 媒体上那么多的暴力事件
And I was starting to get paranoid. All the violence in the medias:
黑帮啦，谋杀啦... 尤其是那连环杀手
Gang violence, murders, especially serial killers...
而最后决定性的原因是...
But the final straw was...
..有天晚上我听到外面消防通道上有些动静
...one night I heard some noise on my fire escape...
于是我打了911，最后警察终于来了
...so I called 9, and the cops came eventually.
- 大概三小时以后吧 - 是啊，那时候我已经被先奸后杀了
- Like three hours later. - Yeah, after I had been raped and killed.
没有啦，来的只是一个男一女两个警察
No, but it was a man and a woman officer.
当那个女警到楼下挪警车的时候
I was explaining what I had heard...
我向他解释我听到的声音
...when the woman had to go move the police car.
那时只有那个男警察和我一起
I was left alone with the male cop.
而他立刻问我是不是有枪... 我说没有，我当然没有了
Right away he asked me if I had a gun, and I said, "No, of course not. "
然后他对我说：“是吗，你最好考虑去买一把”
And he told me, "Well, you better think about getting one.
“这里是美国，不是法国”
This is America, not France. Okay?"
然后我对他说，我完全不懂怎么开枪
And I said to him, "I have no idea how to shoot a gun...
而且，我对枪支也没有兴趣
...and I have no interest in firearms whatsoever. "
于是他抽出他的枪， 就像这样，然后他说：
And that's when he pulled out his gun, like this, and he went:
“总有一天，你会碰到这么个东西指着你的脸”
"Well, one day, you're gonna have something like this in your face...
“如果你想活的长久点”
...and if you wanna have a long life...
“你就必须决定是不是要干掉他们”
...you're gonna have to choose between you or them. "
然后他们就走了，而第二天早上， 我就打电话申请持有枪支
And then they left. And the next morning I called for an application to get a gun.
让我拿把枪！我是说， 那可真可怕...
Me with a gun. I mean, that's really scary.
但是然后我意识到有些事不对劲
But then I realized something was wrong.
那警察拔枪的举动，还有其他的事...
The way that cop had pulled his gun out, and everything, right?
于是我取消了对枪的预订
So I canceled my demand for the gun...
然后我打电话给警察局， 想要对那个警察的行为进行申诉，但是...
...and I called the police and tried to complain about that cop.
- 发生什么事了？ - 要填太多表了
- What happened with that? - It was so much paperwork...
然后我就怕了，就凭我这种学生签证...
...and then I got scared, with my shitty student visa...
- 你认为你会被遣送出境 - 没错！于是我放弃了...
- Thought you'd get deported? - Exactly. I gave up...
然后就忘记了整件事
...and forgot about the whole thing.
- 其实，我想我永远也不会忘记的 - 当然了
- Well, I guess I never forgot. - Obviously.
但是，我真的还是喜欢在那里的日子
But still, you know, I really enjoyed being there.
- 我怀念美国的很多事 - 是吗，比如？
- There's lots of things I miss in the U. S. - Yeah? Like what?
恩...
Well...
那里的人们通常都有好心情
The overall good mood people have there.
比如，你知道的，即使 有的时候胡乱问候
Like, even if it can be bullshit sometimes.
比如“你好吗？”“很好！” “你好吗？”“很好！”
Like, "How you doing?" "Great. " "How you doing?" "Great!"
“祝你今天愉快！”
"Have a great day!"
我也不知道，巴黎人的脾气可不好，你发现了吗？
I don't know. Parisians can be so grumpy. Have you noticed?
没有啊，每个人在我看来都很高兴啊
No, everybody seems pretty happy to me.
- 他们总是不高兴... - 他们总是不高兴？
- They're not happy. No. - They're not happy?
不是，他们也高兴，我不知道 我说的只是法国男人，他们快把我逼疯了！
No, they are. I don't know. I just mean French men. They drive me nuts.
怎么回事？他们怎么了？
What is it? What about them?
恩，他们很好，不深入接触的话非常好
Well, they're very nice. They're great, you know, to be around.
他们喜欢食物，酒 他们做东西很好吃...
They love food, wine, they're great cooks.
但是，不知道，可能我只是运气不好
But I've had really bad luck with them.
怎么这么说？什么意思？
Why? What do you mean?
- 我想他们不是那么... - 怎么？
- Well, I guess they're not as... - What?
怎么说呢
What's the word?
- 好色？他们不那么好色... - 好色？
- Horny? They're not as horny. - Horny?
等等，听我这么说怎样， 对此，我以身为美国人而骄傲
Wait, listen to me on this one. In that regard, I am proud to be an American.
你确实应该如此，仅对此一点
And you should be. In that regard only.
（法语）谢谢
Have you ever spent time in Eastern Europe?
你去过东欧吗？
东欧？没，没有... 谢谢
Eastern... No, I don't. Thank you.
我记得当我十多岁的时候我去过华沙
I remember as a teenager I went to Warsaw...
那时它还是共产主义的那一套
...when it was still a strict communist regime.
- 对此我是一点也不支持 - 当然...
- Which I don't approve of at all. - Sure you don't.
- 不是，我才没有... - 好啦，我只是开玩笑！
- No, I don't. - I'm just kidding.
但是，不管怎样，我发现 待在那里是件很有意思的事
But anyway, something about being there was very interesting.
仅仅几个星期之后 我就有了改变
After a couple of weeks, something changed in me.
那座城市又阴郁又灰暗...
The city was quite gloomy and gray...
但是过了一阵以后，我头脑变的更清醒了
...but after a while, my brain seemed clearer.
我在日记上记录了更多的东西
I was writing more in my journal...
- 很多我以前从来没有过的想法 - 共产主义的想法？
...ideas I'd never thought of before... - Communist ideas?
- 听着，我可不是... - 对不起，我...
- Listen, I'm not... - I'm sorry, I...
- 好吧 - 继续！
- Okay. - Go on.
以后我要送你去俄国古拉格集中营
Okay. I'll send you to a gulag later.
只是，那花了我好一阵时间 才搞清楚为什么那里让人感觉那么不同
No. But it took me a while to figure out why I felt so different.
然后有一天，当我穿过一个犹太墓地的时候
One day, as I was walking through the Jewish cemetery...
我没想通为什么，但是我真的有所改变
...I don't know why, but it occurred to me there...
我意识到过去的两个星期中 我改掉了以前的大多数习惯
...I realized that I had spent the last two weeks away from most of my habits.
电视里说的是我听不懂的语言
TV was in a language I didn't understand...
没什么好买的，也没什么广告
...there was nothing to buy, no advertisements anywhere...
所以，我能做的只有...
...so all I'd been doing was...
到处逛，思考，然后写下来 我的大脑好像在休息
...walk around, think, and write. My brain felt like it was at rest...
没有了那种强烈的情绪 就好像是自然的高潮一样
...free from the consuming frenzy. It was almost like a natural high.
我感觉内心格外平和 没有什么奇怪的冲动要去什么地方
I felt so peaceful inside. No strange urge to be somewhere else...
购物什么的
...to shop...
一开始这样可能看起来很无聊
It could have seemed like boredom at first...
但是很快这就让人感到内心非常非常的充实
...but it became very, very soulful.
非常有意思，你知道吗？
It was interesting, you know?
你能相信我们上一次漫步在维也纳是9年前的事吗？
Can you believe it was nine years ago we were walking around Vienna?
- 九年？真难以想象 - 对我来说就好像是两个月之前的事
- Nine years? No, that's impossible. - No, it was. It feels like two months.
但是那是94年夏天了
But it was summer '94.
我看起来有什么不同吗？
Do I look any different?
有？
I do?
我得看你一丝不挂的样子才知道
I'd have to see you naked.
- 什么？ - 对不起...
- What? - I know, I'm sorry.
你的发型变了，那时...
Your hair was different back then. It was like...
- 什么，一样的啊... - 把头发放下来，让我看看！
- It's the same... Oh, down. - Yeah, take it down.
放下来，好吧，放下来了
Down. Okay, it was down. Okay.
好了
Well? Voil?
怎么样？
So?
快点，告诉我
Okay, come on. Tell me.
瘦了，我觉得，苗条了
Skinnier, I think. A little thinner.
你觉得我以前很胖？
Did you think I was fat before?
- 不是 - 你肯定觉得我那时很胖
- No... - Yeah, you thought I was a fatty.
没错，你觉得我很胖， 你的书写的是个法国胖妞！
No, you thought I was a fatty. You wrote a book about a fat French girl.
- 哦，不要！ - 好啦，说真的
- No, listen. - Oh, no.
你看起来漂亮极了！
Seriously, all right? You look beautiful.
那你觉得我有什么变化吗？
Do I look any different?
没有什么...哦，事实上 你这多了道皱纹
No. Not at all. Actually, you have this line.
- 我知道 - 看起来好像疤
- I know. - It's like a scar.
- 疤？看起来像被枪打得吧？ - 没有，没有，我挺喜欢的，对不起啦
- A scar? Like a gunshot wound? - No, no, no. I like it. I'm sorry.
有天我做了个有趣的... 呃，不，恐怖的梦
I had this funny... Well, horrible dream the other day.
我做恶梦，梦见我有32岁了
I was having this awful nightmare that I was 32.
然后当我醒来的时候，我才只有23！ 我就放心了...
And then I woke up, and I was 23. So relieved.
但是后来我真的从梦里醒来， 发现我确实32了
And then I woke up for real, and I was 32.
- 好可怕！ - 是会有这种事的
- Shit, man. It happens. - Scary.
时间越走越快，看上去，是因为...
Time goes faster and faster. Apparently, it's because...
从20岁以后我们身体里的神经键就不再更新了 于是，从那以后我们就开始走下坡路了
...we don't renew synapses after our 20s, so it's downhill from then on.
我喜欢变老，你懂吗，会感觉生活更...
I like getting older, you know? Life feels...
我不知道，好像感觉更直接 好像我能欣赏更多东西了
I don't know, it feels more immediate. Like I can appreciate things more.
其实我也一样，我很喜欢
No, me too, actually. I really love it.
我曾经是...
I was once...
一个乐队里的鼓手
...a drummer in a band.
- 真的？ - 是啊，我们当时真的很棒
- You were? - Yeah. We were pretty good, actually.
不过那个主唱，他整天就想着让我们能出唱片
But the lead-singer guy, he was just so obsessed with us getting a record deal.
我们整天谈的，想的 就是参加更大的演出
It's all we talked about, thought about, getting bigger shows.
每时每刻都是为了将来的发展，而现在...
Everything was just focused on the future all the time. And now...
...乐队却已经不存在了
...the band doesn't even exist anymore.
现在回顾那些我们参加了的表演
And looking back at the shows we did play...
甚至哪怕只是排练 都觉得那么有意思！
...even rehearsing, it was just so much fun.
现在我终于能享受那每一分钟了 我能抽一口吗？
I just... Now I'd enjoy every minute of it. Could I have a drag of that?
你的书出版了，这事不算小了
Well, your book has been published. That's a pretty big deal.
而且你巡回了整个欧洲来卖它 你觉得能享受其中的每一分钟吗？
You've been all around Europe. Are you enjoying every minute of it?
- 不太行... - 不太行？
- Not really. - Not really?
不行
No.
- 你还有烟吗？ - 当然有
- Do you have another one of those? - Yes, of course.
给你
Here.
在我这行里，我见到很多人... 哦，对不起...
In my field, I see these people that... Oh, sorry.
过于理想，好高骛远
Come into it with big, idealist visions...
想要成为新的领袖， 来创建更美好的世界
...of becoming the leader that will create a better world.
他们乐于见到目标被实现， 却对过程没兴趣！
They enjoy the goal, but not the process.
- 是啊 - 但事实上...
- Right. - But the reality of it is...
真正能改善世界的工作 是日复一日的点滴进步
...the true work of improving things is in the little achievements.
- 这才是应该享受的事 - 你具体指什么呢？
- That's what you need to enjoy. - What do you mean, exactly?
比如，我为一个组织工作 这个组织在墨西哥帮助那里的村民
I was working for this organization that helped villages in Mexico.
他们关心的是怎么把铅笔
And their concerns was how to get the pencils...
送到那些乡村小学的孩子手中
...sent to the kid in those little country schools.
那不是什么重大的革命性的想法 仅仅是铅笔而已！
It was not about big, revolutionary ideas. It was about pencils.
我见到过那些做实事的人 很不幸的是...
I see the people that do the real work, and what's really sad is that...
...那些最慷慨的，最勤劳的...
...the people that are the most giving, hardworking...
...也是最能让这个世界变得更好的人...
...and capable of making this world better...
...往往没什么野心 不想成为什么领袖
...usually don't have the ego and ambition to be a leader.
他们对那些形式上的奖励没有兴趣
They don't see any interest in superficial rewards.
他们也不在乎自己的名字能不能上报纸
They don't care if their name ever appear in the press.
他们只是享受着帮助人的那种过程
They actually enjoy the process of helping others.
- 他们自得其乐 - 是啊，不过那很难啊！
- They're in the moment. - Yeah, but that's so hard...
自得其乐，我是说，我感觉我好像...
...you know, to be in the moment. I mean, I feel like I'm...
是被设计成那种对什么都不很满意的类型...
...designed to be slightly dissatisfied with everything, you know?
你懂吗，我是说，好像永远都 在试图改善自己的现状一样
It's like always trying to better my situation.
我满足了一种欲望 就会刺激另一种欲望，懂吗？
I satisfy one desire, and it just agitates another.
然后我就想：都去他妈的吧 欲望是生活的动力
And then I think, to hell with it, right? Desire's the fuel of life.
你认为这是真的吗？
You know? Do you think it's true...
如果我们没有欲望，我们就会永远快乐？
...that if we never wanted anything, we'd never be unhappy?
我不知道，没有欲望，这难道 不是抑郁症的一种表现吗？
I don't know. Not wanting anything, isn't that a symptom of depression?
没错，就是的，对吧？ 我是说，有欲望是种健康的表现，对吧？
Yeah, that is, right? I mean, it's healthy to desire, right?
是啊，我不知道，不过那些佛教徒都那么说，对吧？
Yeah. I don't know. It's what all those Buddhist guys say, right?
从欲望中解脱出来，你就会发现...
Liberate yourself from desire, and you'll find...
- 你已经拥有你需要的一切 - 是啊，不过当我想要拥有...
...you already have everything you need. - But I feel alive...
那些不算基本生存需要的东西的时候 我能感觉到自己是真实存活的
...when I want something more than basic survival needs.
我是说，不管哪种欲望，比如想和谁亲热
Wanting, whether it's intimacy with another person...
或是想要双新鞋，都很美...
...or a pair of shoes, is beautiful.
我喜欢我们拥有无止境的欲望
I like that we have those ever-renewing desires, you know?
也许那是一种有权享用的感觉
Maybe it's this sense of entitlement.
你懂吗，好像什么时候你觉得你配穿双新鞋
You know, like whenever you feel like you deserve that new pair of shoes?
欲望本身不是坏事，只要你不要 太在意得失就好
It's okay to want things, as long as you aren't pissed off if you don't get them.
生活很辛苦，这也是顺理成章的事
Life's hard. It's supposed to be.
吃一堑，长一智，对吗？
If we didn't suffer, we wouldn't learn a thing, you know?
那，你是佛教徒吗？
So, what, are you Buddhist, or something?
- 不是 - 不是？为什么不是？
- No. - No? Why not?
我不知道，出于同一原因， 我不会让自己完全相信任何信仰
I don't know. The same reason I don't really consider myself anything, really.
很久前我就决定 我可以接受任何信念...
I decided a long time ago that I was gonna be open to everything...
但是不会执迷于一种信仰
...but not buy into any one and only belief system.
数年前，我曾经去过一所苦修派修道院
I went to this Trappist monastery a couple years ago.
- 苦修派？ - 是的，天主教西多教派的
- Trappist? - Yeah, they're Catholic. Cistercian.
- 你为什么要去那 - 为什么？可能就是去读些书吧
- Why did you do that? - Why? I'd been doing some reading.
我觉得那很酷，你曾经和修士和修女生活在一起过吗？
Thought it'd be cool. Have you ever spent any time with monks or nuns?
- 没有，我可不想那样 - 没有？
- No. It's not really my style. - No?
我本来以为他们都是神情肃穆 严厉苛刻的，但是他们不是
Well, I expected them to be all glowering and stern, but they weren't.
他们很容易就笑，非常好相处
They were quick to laugh, really easy to be around.
真的，他们对一切都不排斥 他们只是...
Seriously, very attuned to everything, they were just...
你懂吗，他们不会打扰任何人
You know, they weren't trying to hustle anybody.
他们只是想平静的信奉天主 生存，然后死去
They're trying to live and die in peace with God...
也或者他们信奉的是其他什么 他们觉得永恒的东西
...or whatever part of them they feel is eternal.
但是身处其间真的很舒服
It was just so refreshing to be around.
你懂吗，你会发现你遇到的绝大多数人
You realize that most of the people that you meet...
都是想要过的更好
...are trying to get somewhere better.
赚更多的钱啦 赢得更多的尊敬啊，
They're trying to make more cash, get a little more respect...
让人们崇拜自己啊之类的 太累了！
...have more people admire them. It's exhausting.
- 没错 - 要是你自己也成为这样的人，真是太累了
- No kidding. - And it's exhausting to be one yourself.
我是说，我就是这样的，精神上很贪婪
There I am, right, you know, all greedy to be more spiritual.
我想变得更好，懂吗，这是你逃不脱的！
"I want to be a better person," you know? You can't escape.
好多年前，我有个男友想做佛教徒
I had this boyfriend of mine many years ago that wanted to be a Buddhist.
然后他去了亚洲，去瞻仰那里的寺院
So he went to Asia to visit some of those monasteries.
- 是啊，我也想过去那些地方 - 那你应该去，我告诉你为什么
- I've thought about doing that too. - Yeah, you should. I'll tell you why.
啊，他长得很帅 每次他去那些寺院的时候
He was good-looking, and each time he went to one of the monasteries...
都会有僧侣愿意替他口交
...a monk offered to suck his cock.
真的
True story.
好吧，最后都会变成这样，对吧？
It all comes down to that, doesn't it?
我是说，这就是为什么我很崇拜你做的事
That's why I really admire what you're doing.
你什么意思，口交？
- You know? - What do you mean? Sucking cock?
- 啊，不... - 不是？我猜错了？
- No. - No? Wrong answer.
不是，我想说的是，你不是那种超然的人
No, I was gonna say you're not detached from life.
你做事很有激情
You're putting your passion into action.
这个嘛，起码我努力这样做
Well, I try.
你知道吗，我接下来8个小时会在机场
You know something? I'm gonna be on planes...
以及飞机上度过
...and in an airport for the next eight hours...
我很想再看看巴黎
I'd just love to see a little bit more of Paris.
- 我们能出去走走... - 好啊，好啊，我们走吧！
- Would you walk with me? - Yeah.
- 你介意吗？ - 怎么会呢，很好啊！
- Do you mind? - That's great.
- 你想去吗？ - 当然！
- Do you want to? - Let's do that. Yeah.
我们该付多少？4块5...
What do we owe here? Four-fifty?
不用，不用，我有，我有
No, I got it, I got a little per diem going on here.
- 这够付小费的了吗？ - 恩，够了
- This good, for a tip? - Yeah, that's fine.
- 只多不少！ - 这个也留下吧
- That's more than enough. - Throw that in too.
- 好啦，周围有什么值得逛的吗？ - 今天是减价日！
- Is there anywhere to go around here? - It's sales day today.
- 什么意思？ - 今天巴黎什么东西都会减价
- What's that? - It's when everything's on sale in Paris.
每年两次
It's twice a year.
（法语）再见，谢谢
（法语）再见
All right, let's go shopping.
好啊，那我们去购物吧！
不，不，这主意不好 我不想让你这样
No, no, no. That's a bad idea. I don't wanna inflict that on you.
那简直疯了，我们就去那个 花园逛逛吧，那真的不错的
It's madness. Let's just go to this garden path. It's really nice.
好啊，听起来其实比购物要好
All right. That sounds better than shopping, actually.
我是说，我并不是不想陪你做你喜欢的事
Not that I wouldn't do whatever you wanted.
其实有的时候我也不是需要什么东西
Sometimes I don't even need to buy anything. I just get high...
我只是想试穿，还有看那些商品， 这让我很兴奋
...on trying on and looking at things.
这个嘛，苦修派僧侣会对你说... 我们往这边走？
Is this where we're going?
- 是的！ - 苦修派僧侣会对你说这很好
- Yeah. - A therapist will tell you that's good.
- 真的？ 你节食过吗？ - 没有！
- Really? Are you ever in therapy? - Oh, no.
- 我看起来像在节食吗？ - 我只是开玩笑
- Do I seem like I'm in therapy? - I'm kidding.
- 这对你的性障碍有帮助吗？ - 我的性障碍？
- Does it help your sex problems? - My sex problems?
- 没有啦，我只是开玩笑 - 比如呢？跟我说实话
- I'm kidding. - Tell me the truth.
- 那天晚上我们不是挺好的？ - 不，我是在开玩笑
- We didn't have any problems. - No, I'm kidding.
- 我们根本就没有做爱 - 这是个玩笑，对吧？
- We didn't even have sex. - That's a joke, right?
不是，我们确实没做爱！ 就是这么回事
No, we didn't. I mean, that was the whole thing.
- 可我们确实做了啊！ - 没有，没有，我们没做！
- Of course we did. - No, no, no, we didn't.
你没有安全套， 而我没有安全套从来不做爱
You didn't have a condom and I never have sex without one.
尤其是一夜情那种，我是说， 我对于自己的健康非常在意，我不可能...
I'm extremely paranoid. There's no way...
我觉得这太可怕了， 你竟然不记得我们之间发生过什么
I find it scary that you don't remember what happened.
不，听我说
No, listen...
...我从来没写过一整本书 但是我记日记...
...I didn't write an entire book, but I kept a journal...
我在里面记下了整晚发生的事
...and I wrote the whole night in it. That's what I meant, you idealizing it.
这就是我的意思，你对 那夜进行了理想化的加工！
好啦，听我说！我甚至记得 我们用过的安全套是什么牌子的
All right, listen, I even remember what brand of condom we used.
好啦，这太恶心啦，我不想听！
That's disgusting. I don't wanna hear it.
- 这有什么恶心的... - 没有啦
- That's not disgusting. - No.
好啦，等我回家，我会查我94年的日记 不过我知道我是对的！
Okay, when I get home I'll check my journal from '94, but I know I'm right.
- 等等... - 怎么了？
- Wait a minute. - What?
- 那是在一个墓地发生的吗？ - 不是...
- Was it in the cemetery? - No.
不是的，我们是下午去那个墓地的
No, we went to the cemetery in the afternoon.
应该是在一个公园里，深夜时分
It was in the park, very late at night.
- 在公园里！ - 等等...
- In the park? - Wait a minute, wait a minute.
我真不能...我没法...
I can't... I can't...
这事这么容易忘记吗？ 你真的不记得了？在公园里！
Is it that forgettable? You really don't remember? In the park?
好的，等等 我想你可能是对的...
Okay. Wait a minute, I think you might be right...
行啦，你在和我胡扯是不是
You're messing with me now.
- 没有 - 你在和我胡扯吗？
- No. - Are you messing with me?
不是的，对不起！我觉得你... 我是说，你是对的，这样可以了吧？
Okay. No, I'm sorry. I think... I mean, you're right, okay?
有时我就是忘事
Sometimes I put things in drawers inside my head and forget about it.
我想有时忘记会让人少些痛苦！
It's less painful to put things away than live with it.
什么，就是说那夜对你来说是段很难过的回忆罗？
What, so that night was, like, a sad memory for you?
不，我不是针对那一夜
I didn't mean that night in particular.
我只是说有些事情还是忘了好
I meant certain things are better forgotten.
那夜是我那一整年记的最清楚的一天
I remember that night better than I do entire years.
- 我也是 - 真的吗？
- Me too. - Really?
呃，我觉得我是...
Well, I thought I did.
不过，可能我...可能我忘记那事是因为...
But maybe I... Maybe I put it away because of the fact that...
...我祖母葬礼的那天 就是我们约好再见的那天
...my grandmother's funeral was the day we were supposed to meet.
对我来说那天挺难熬 不过对你来说大概更糟
It was a tough day for me, but it must've been worse for you.
感觉好像不真实，我还记得我看见她的遗体躺在棺材里
It was unreal. I remember looking at her dead body in the coffin...
她曾经总是用她美丽的手抱着我 那么温暖，那么亲切...
...at her beautiful hands, so warm, so sweet, that used to hold me...
但是棺材里的她 和我记忆中的一点都不一样
...but nothing in that coffin resembled what I remembered of her.
所有的温暖都消逝了
All the warmth was gone.
然后我开始哭... 我感觉很困惑，不知道
And then I was crying, so confused if I was crying...
我哭是因为不能再见到她了 还是因为不能再见到你了
...because I was never gonna see her again or never gonna see you again...
对不起， 我竟然变成这样 这个星期我情绪都有点低落，我不知道...
I'm sorry. I'm sorry to go on like this. I've been a little down this week.
- 为什么？ - 我不知道，没什么，只是...
- Why? - I don't know. Nothing bad, just...
可能是因为读了你的书？
Reading your book, maybe?
也不是，不过...想想那个夏天和秋天， 我充满了希望
No, but... Thinking of how hopeful I was that summer and fall...
而自从那以后，好像就有点...
...and since then it's been kind of a...
我也不知道
I don't know.
回忆本来是非常美好的 只要你能让过去的都过去
Memory is a wonderful thing if you don't have to deal with the past.
"Memory is wonderful if you don't have to deal with the past. "
我能把这话贴到我车牌上吗？
Can I put that on a bumper sticker?
你知道吗？要是你写一本关于我们的一夜情的书 这是个不错的书名！
If you wrote a book about our night, that's a good title.
- 可能会是本完全不同的书 - 是啊，不会涉及色情
- And it could be a total different book. - Yeah, there'd be no sex scenes.
- 不过你知道吗？ - 恩？
- But you know what? - What?
既然现在我们又见面了
Now that we've met again...
我们可以改变我们那个12月16日的回忆
...we can change our memory of that December 6.
那回忆将不再有是以悲剧结尾了， 因为我们又见面了
It no longer has that sad ending of us never seeing each other again.
没错，我想回忆永远可以更改 只要你还活着...
Right. I mean, I guess a memory's never finished as long as you're alive.
是啊，我知道，我有一段童年的回忆
Yeah, I know. I have this memory from my childhood...
- 但是我最近意识到，这段回忆其实从未发生过 - 是什么？
...I realized recently never happened. - What?
这个，当我八九岁的时候 我妈妈很担心
Well, when I was 8 or 9, my mom was so paranoid...
...怕我上完钢琴课以后 一个人走回家会出事...
...when I was walking home from my piano lesson at night...
...她总是让我当心 色迷迷的的老头给我糖果...
...she'd warn me about dirty old men giving me candies...
...然后给我看他们的鸡鸡
...and then showing me their pee-pees.
她总是这么说 然后后来，你懂吗，我...
She was so obsessed with it that, later in life, you know...
...我头脑中就真的觉得这曾经发生过！
...I had this image in my head that this really happened.
我甚至把做爱和回家联系到一起了
To the point that I even associated sex with that walk home.
我是说，有时候，甚至是现在，当我...
I mean, and sometimes, even now, when I'm...
当我做爱的时候，我都好像 看见我自己在那街上走
When I'm having sex, I see myself walking down that street.
我发誓！非常奇怪，对吧？
I swear. It's so weird, right?
- 呃，那条街离这近吗？我是说，能... - 不行
- Is that street nearby? I mean, could...? - Could we? No.
非常远
Very far.
你小的时候记日记吗？
Did you ever keep a journal when you were a kid?
恩，算是吧，有时记
Yeah. On and off, I guess.
很有意思的是，我有天读了...
It's funny, I read one of mine...
- 我83年的一本日记 - 怎么了
...from '83 the other day. - Yeah?
让我惊奇的是
And what really surprised me is...
我那时的人生观和现在一样
...that I was dealing with life the same way I am now.
当然我那时更天真，更充满希望
I was much more hopeful and naive...
...不过内心深处对事情的感觉是完全一样的！
...but the core, and the way I was feeling things, is exactly the same.
这让我意识到我其实没怎么变
It made me realize I haven't changed much at all.
是啊，谁不是这样的呢？
I don't think anybody does.
尽管人们都不愿意承认，但事实上我们... 我们很多个性都是天生的
People don't want to admit it, but it's like we have these innate set points...
很少有什么后天发生的事 能改变我们的性情
...and nothing much that happens to us changes our disposition.
- 你是这么想的？ - 是的
- You believe that? - I think so.
我曾经读过一些研究报告 是关于那些赢了彩票的人...
I read this study where they followed people who'd won the lottery...
...和截瘫的人的心态
...and people who'd become paraplegics.
你会认为前一件事能让你欣喜若狂， 后一件则让你简直想自杀
You'd think one extreme is gonna make you euphoric and the other suicidal.
但是研究却表明，大概六个月之后
But the study shows that, after about six months...
只要人们习惯了他们的新处境
...as soon as people had gotten used to their new situation...
- 他们就和以前差不多一样了 - 一样？
...they were, more or less, the same. - The same?
恩，是的，如果他们本质上是乐观开朗的人
Yeah. Like, if they were basically an optimistic, jovial person...
即使他们现在坐在了轮椅上，他们还是乐天派
...they're now an optimistic, jovial person in a wheelchair.
如果他们是见识短浅的笨家伙
If they're a petty, miserable asshole...
就算他们有了卡迪拉克轿车，大房子 游艇，他们还是见识短浅的笨蛋
...they're a petty, miserable asshole with a new Cadillac, a house and a boat.
就是说，哪怕有再多的幸运降临 他们还是难以得到满足？
So I'll be forever depressed no matter what great things happen?
- 没错！ - 好吧
- Definitely. - Great.
别开玩笑了，你现在郁闷吗？
No, come on, are you depressed now?
不，不，我不郁闷
No, no, I'm not depressed.
不过有的时候我会担心 当我走到生命尽头的时候...
But sometimes I worry I'll get to the end of my life...
-...我会发现我想要做的事还没都做过 - 哦，那你想要做什么？
...feeling I haven't done all I wanted to. - Well, what do you want to do?
我....
I...
我想画更多的画 我想每天弹吉他
I want to paint more, I want to play my guitar every day.
我想学中文 我想写更多的歌...
I want to learn Chinese. I want to write more songs.
我想做的事太多了 但是最后却只干了没多少
There's so many things I want to do, and I end up doing not much.
好吧，那，让我问你这个问题： 你相信，恩，比如鬼或者灵魂什么的吗？
All right, well, let me ask you this: Do you believe in ghosts or spirits?
呃，不信
No.
- 不信？ - 不信
- No? - No.
- 好，那投胎呢？ - 一点不信
- Okay, what about reincarnation? - Not at all.
- 上帝呢？ - 不信
- God? - No.
- 好吧 - 听起来挺惨的吧
- All right. - That sounds terrible. No, no, no.
不过，同时呢，我不想变成那种不相信任何魔力的人
But I don't want to be one of those people that don't believe in any magic.
- 你相信占星术 - 没错！
- So then, astrology? - Yes, of course!
- 总算找到一样了 - 我是说，这很有道理，对吧？
- There we go. - That makes sense, right?
你是天蝎，我是射手，所以我们合得来
You're a Scorpio, I'm a Sag, we get along.
没有啦
No, no, no.
爱因斯坦说过一段话，我真的很喜欢
There's an Einstein quote I really, really like.
他说：“如果你不相信任何魔法和神话的话
He said, "If you don't believe in any kind of magic or mystery
- 那你就和死人差不多了” - 是啊，我也喜欢这话
you're basically as good as dead. " - Yeah, I like that.
我总是觉得茫茫宇宙中有些神秘的和谐
I've always felt there was some kind of mystical core to the universe.
最近我在想有关我啊，我的性格之类的
But, more recently, I've started to think that, me, my personality, whatever...
我不能永远待在这里
That I don't have any permanent place here, you know.
我们不会长生不老
In eternity or whatever, you know.
我越想到这个，就越觉得不能浪费人生
And the more I think that, I can't go through life saying this is no big deal.
因为生命仅此一次 任何事情，不管是有趣的
This is it. This is actually happening. What do you think is interesting?
还是好笑的 或者是重要的
What do you think is funny? What is important?
懂吗，每天都有可能是我们的最后一天
You know, every day's our last.
我一想到这个，我就会打电话给我的妈妈说我有多爱她
When I feel that way, I usually call my mom to tell her I love her.
- 是吗 - 然后她就总问
- Yeah? - And she's always:
“你还好吧”“你不会得了癌症吧？ 你会去自杀吗？”
"Are you okay? Do you have cancer? Are you gonna commit suicide?"
不至于吧
It's almost not worth it.
那我们呢
So, what about us?
- 我们？ - 我是说
- What about us? - No, what I mean is...
- 如果我们今晚就要死了 - 你是说世界末日来临？
...if we were both going to die tonight... - Like the apocalypse was coming?
不，没有那么恐怖 ，不过， 如果只有我们两个要死了
No, that's too dramatic... But what if just the two of us were going to die?
我们还会谈论你的书吗？
I mean, would we talk about your book?
- 或者环境问题吗？ - 如果今天是我们的最后一天？
- The environment? Or... - If today was our last day?
没错，我们会谈什么，你会跟我说什么？
Yeah, what would we talk about? What would you tell me?
- 恩 - 很难回答？
- Well... - That's hard, huh?
- 不不，我在想呢 - 好吧
- No, no, I'll do it. - Okay.
我一定不会再讨论我的书了
I definitely would stop talking about my book.
- 我得承认我大概也不会谈环境问题了 - 好
- I would probably drop the environment. - Okay.
不过我仍然想要谈谈 那些魔法啊，宇宙什么的
But I would still want to talk about, you know, the magic in the universe.
- 只是我希望做这些的时候我是在一个...． - 什么？
- I'd just want to do it from a... - What?
...一个旅馆房间里...
...a hotel room, you know...
...在我们每个疯狂做爱的间隙 直到我们死去
...in between sessions of us wildly fucking until we die.
哇！何必要浪费时间去旅馆呢？
Wow. Well, why waste time with an hotel room?
为什么不在这儿？在这张长椅上？
Why not do it right there on a bench?
- 不 - 来，过来
Come here, come here, come here.
好啦，我们不会今晚就死的
Okay. We're not gonna die tonight.
好吧，我太激动了，对不起
All right. Too bad. I'm sorry.
我举的只是一个极端的例子
That was an extreme example.
- 对不起 - 没事
- I'm sorry. - Okay.
我想要说的是...
What I... My point was, you know...
我很难和别人深层次地沟通
...to truly communicate with people is very hard to do.
我懂，不像日常的交流...
No, I know, most of our day-to-day exchanges...
我知道，我是说...
Yeah, no, I mean...
- 不要把什么都跟性扯上关系 - 为什么不呢？
...not to bring everything back to sex... - But why not?
不，举个例子来说吧， 我的一个女朋友
No, this example, this friend of mine, she was talking about...
- 她曾和我说起她跟她男朋友在床上的问题 - 然后呢
- She and her boyfriend... Problems in bed. - Right.
她说他们交往一年之后，她开始告诉他...
And how when they had been dating for a year she started telling him...
...怎样才能让她获得更多的快感 而这让她男友非常生气！
...what he could do to please her more, and it freaked him out.
- 为什么？ - 他很生气
- Why? - Totally.
他觉得这是说自己做得不好
He thought it meant he was a bad lover...
也许她不该等这么久才说
Maybe she shouldn't have waited so long.
- 你知道，一年以后... - 没错，不过男人也太容易被激怒了！
- After a year... - But men are so easily offended.
- 你觉得比女人还容易？ - 当然了，在这一点上毫无疑问！
- What, more than women? - Definitely on that subject.
- 你这么觉得？ - 没错
- You think so? - Yeah, yeah.
也许这是因为
Well, maybe it's because, you know...
- 男人比较容易获得满足 - 获得满足？
...men are easier to... To please. - To please?
- 我不知道 - 没错，他们绝对是的
- Well, I don't know. - Yeah, they are. They're definitely.
总之我的朋友对我说
Anyway, this friend, she was telling me...
...下次她再交男朋友她会给他做一个问卷...
...next time she dates a man, she's gonna make a little questionnaire...
- 问明什么是他们喜欢的和不喜欢的 - 你是说写下来还是大声问？
...about what they like and dislike... - What, written down, or out loud?
当然是写下来
Yeah, mostly written down.
不过答案不仅仅是“是”或“否” 应该要更详细一点
But it wouldn't be just yes or no. It would be a bit more complex than that.
打个比方，如果问题是 “你喜欢性虐待吗？”
Like, for example, if the question is: "Are you into S & M?"
答案可以是: “不，但是偶尔为之也不错”
The answer could be: "No, but a good spanking once in a while doesn't hurt. "
- 怎么样？ - 好，或者是“你喜欢在做爱时讲一些激发情欲的话吗？”
Right, or like: "Do you like talking dirty in bed?"
- 类似这种问题？ - 对，不过不只是这么泛泛的
- That kind of thing? - Yeah, but not just like any dirty talk.
要说：“你喜欢听什么样的词”？
Just "What specific word would you like to hear?"
- 你是问我吗？ - 恩，是啊
- What, me? - Well, yeah.
比如你喜欢听什么样的话？
For example what specific word would you like to hear?
我不知道
I don't know.
你觉得“小蜜桃”这词怎样？
What do you feel about the word "pussy"?
我很喜欢
I love it.
很好
Good.
没想到九年之后我们都变得这么现实了
It's amazing what perverts we've become in the past nine years.
至少我们现不用把每次新的性体验...
At least now we don't have to pretend each new sexual experience...
...都当作是是改变我们人生的大事
...is, like, a life-altering event.
我知道，你已经有过了那么多次感情经历 现在都快失去激情了
I know. By now, you've stuck it in so many places it's about to fall off.
我也没指望你会一直想着我
And I can't realistically expect you've become anything but a total ho.
- 哦，谢谢 - 不，我很抱（歉）...
- Yeah, thank you. - No, I'm s...
- 没错阿，你该怎样呢？ - 我该...
- That's true. What can you do? - What can you do?
对了，你平时都写些什么歌？ 我还不知道你会写歌呢
So, what kind of songs do you write? I didn't know you did that.
- 什么类型的？ - 是啊
- What kind? - Yeah, sure.
- 我不知道，只是歌而已 - 比如
- I don't know, just songs. - Like?
比如有些是有关人的
Like, some are about, you know, people.
恩，或是各种爱恨情仇... 还有一首是写我的猫猫的！
Relationships. One's about my cat.
- 唱首听听！ - 不行，我没有吉他
- Sing one. - No, I can't. I don't have a guitar.
- 来吧，清唱一首 - 不行，不行
- Come on. A cappella. - No, no, no.
没有吉他伴奏我唱不了歌 你太过分了！
I'm not singing a song without a guitar. You're nuts.
为什么？
Why not?
- 好吧，至少不是现在 - 就一首
- No, okay. Not now. No. - One.
如果不是现在，还有什么时候呢？ 你想六个月后在这儿见面吗？带着吉他？
If not now, when? You want to meet here in six months with a guitar?
我会飞过来的
I'll fly all the way over here.
- 但你不一定能赶上地铁 - 好啦，这不好笑
- You may or may not make the M閠ro. - Okay, that's funny.
- 我们该回书店了！ - 没事的
- We've got to get back. - We'll be all right.
- 你会错过你的航班的，快点！ - 好吧
- You're gonna miss your flight. - All right.
我们可以沿塞纳河走走，很漂亮的
We can walk down La Seine. It's nice.
好吧
Okay.
- 那你是要飞回纽约吗？ - 是的
- So you're flying back to New York? - Yeah, yeah.
我在文章中读到你结婚了， 还有了一个孩子，真是太好了！
So I read in that article that you're married with a kid. That's great.
没错，他已经... 他已经四岁了
Yeah, he's... He's 4.
- 他叫什么？ - 亨利，小汉克
- What's his name? - Henry. Little Hank.
- 他很可爱 - 当然了
- He's so much fun. - Oh, wow, I'm sure.
- 你的太太呢？她是做什么的？ - 她在小学教书
- Your wife, what does she do? - She teaches elementary school.
- 你有孩子吗？ - 是的，有两个。糟了！
- Do you have kids? - Yes, two... Shit!
- 怎么了？ - 我把他们落在车上了！
- What? - I left them in the car!
窗关得死死的，快有六个月了... 他们会有事吗？
With the windows up, six months ago! Think they're okay?
没有啦，我开玩笑的 不过我很想要小孩
No, I'm kidding. No, but I want to have kids someday.
- 只是还没做好准备 - 没有吗？
- I'm just not ready yet. - No?
- 不过我现在正在认真谈恋爱 - 噢是吗？这很好啊
- I'm in a good relationship, though. - Oh yeah? That's good.
- 他是做什么的？ - 他是个摄影记者
- What's he do? - He's a photojournalist.
专门做战地新闻
He does war coverage.
他经常出差，不过从某种角度对我来说 是一件好事，因为我实在是太忙了
He's away a lot, which is good because I'm so busy.
不过那不是很危险吗？ 我是说，不是有很多人在战争中丧生吗？
But isn't that dangerous? Aren't a lot of those guys getting killed these days?
他向我保证不会太冒险的 不过我还是会经常担心
He promises me he doesn't take risks, but I often worry.
他一拿起相机就什么都不顾了
He goes in this trance when he photographs something.
- 什么意思？ - 有一次我们在新德里
- What do you mean? - Well, once we were in New Delhi...
见到一个流浪汉，他躺在人行道上
...and we passed a bum on the...
- 炸弹（谐音）？ - 流浪汉！无家可归的人
- A bomb? - A bum. A homeless.
哦，流浪汉
All right, right.
总之他看起来需要帮助， 但是我男朋友的第一个反应就是拿起相机！
He looked like he needed help, but his first reaction was to photograph him.
他凑到离那个人的脸非常近的地方 整理他的衣领，让他看起来显得更精神
He went really close to his face, fixing his collar...
他似乎完全不在乎那个人
...totally detached from the person.
不过要做好工作不就得这样吗？
But don't you have to be like that to be good at that job?
是啊，我知道啊，我不是...
Yeah, I mean, I'm not...
我不是由此来看他的为人 他的工作是重要的也是高尚的
I'm not judging him. What he does is essential and incredible.
我只是说这是我自己永远做不到的
All I'm saying is that I could never do it.
我们上那船吧！快！
Let's get on that boat. Come on.
- 不！ - 快，很有趣的！
- No! - Come on, it'll be fun.
- 你没时间了！我们得走了 - 它就要开了
- You don't have time! - They're about to take off.
我还有15分钟呢 你有手机吗？
I've got 5 more minutes. Do you have a cell phone?
- 有 - 那就好，我有那个司机的号码
- Yeah. - All right, I've got that driver's number.
我可以打电话给他 让他在下一站停船的地方接我们
I can call him to pick us up at the next stop.
好吧，可我从来没上过那船， 这是给游客的，太丢脸了
I've never been on those boats. It's for tourists, it's embarrassing.
好啦，没事的
Okay. All right.
（法语）- 唔，我们可以上船了吗？ - 当然
- （法语）请给我两张票！ - 不，让我来，让我来
No, I'll get it, I'll get it.
- （法语）不，不，还是我来吧 - 好吧，好吧，好吧
All right. All right, all right.
- （法语）下一站停在哪里？ - （法语）亨利四世码头
谢谢
Thank you.
- 那你现在是跟他沉浸在爱河里咯？ - 谁？
- So are you in love with that guy? - What guy?
- 那个战地摄影师 - 哦，当然！
- The war photographer. - Yes, of course.
（法语）- 你们可以进去了 - 谢谢
对不起，你的手机...
So do you have that cell phone?
哦，对
Oh, yeah.
- 好，让我看看他的号码.... - 好
- Okay, let's see... - Okay.
我该怎么跟他说呢？
What do I tell him?
让他在亨利四世码头等着
Tell him to pick you up at Quai Henri Quatre.
哦，见鬼，什么码头？
Oh, shit. Quai...?
亨利四世，亨利四世码头
Henri Quatre. Quai Henri Quatre.
亨利四世
Henri Quatre.
你怎么了？不对，你要我来说吗？ 亨利四世
What's wrong with you? No, do you want me to...? Henri Quatre.
- 亨利四世？ - 没错！
- Henry Four? - Yes!
- 那你为什么不直接说？ - 对不起！
- Come on, why didn't you say so? - I'm sorry. Okay.
你好，是菲利普吗？
Yeah, is this Philippe?
菲利普，我是杰西·华莱士
Yeah. Philippe, this is Jesse Wallace.
对
Yeah.
呃，听我说，我现在在一条游船上
Well, listen, I'm on one of those boats, right?
我们将会在亨利四世码头下船
And we're gonna arrive at Henry Four.
亨利四号码头 你知道在哪儿吗？
At Port Henry Four. You know what that is?
很好，你带着我的行李吧？
All right, great. And you have my bags, right?
我们再过...总之下一站就到了
Yeah, so we'll be there in... I don't know, it's the next stop.
好，再见
Okay. Au revoir.
- 安排好了？ - 恩
- It's okay? - Yeah, yeah.
哇！
Oh, wow.
- 看这边啊，巴黎圣母院！ - 哇
- Notre Dame, man. Check that out. - Oh, wow.
我听过一个故事 说的是占领巴黎的德军
I heard this story once about when the Germans were occupying Paris...
...撤出的时候
...and they had to retreat back.
他们在巴黎圣母院埋了很多炸药
They wired Notre Dame to blow...
...但他们得留一个人来按爆破的按钮
...but they had to leave one guy in charge of hitting the switch.
但那个人，那个士兵 他却下不了手！
And the guy, the soldier, he couldn't do it.
他只是呆呆地坐着 惊叹这地方的美妙
He just sat there, knocked out by how beautiful the place was.
当盟军部队到达的时候
Then, when the Allied troops came in...
他们发现炸药还在那里 但按钮没人碰过
...they found all the explosives lying there and the switch unturned...
同样的情景还发生在 圣心堂，埃菲尔铁塔...
...and they found the same thing at the Sacr?Coeur, Eiffel Tower...
...很多地方
...couple other places, I think.
这是真的吗？
Is that true?
我不知道 不过我一直很喜欢这个故事
I don't know. I always liked the story, though.
没错，很震撼的一个故事
Yeah, that's a great story.
你相信巴黎圣母院有一天会消失吗？
But you have to think that Notre Dame will be gone one day.
这里曾经是另一座教堂，就在这
There used to be another church at the Seine, right there.
- 什么，同一个地方？ - 是的
- What, right in the same spot? - Yeah.
这样好舒服，我从来没有试过！
You know, this is great. I've never done this.
- 是啊 - 我已经忘了巴黎有多美
- Yeah. - I forget about how beautiful Paris is.
其实当个游客也不错
It's not so bad, being a tourist.
- 谢谢你带我上这船 - 不用客气
- Thanks for getting me on the boat. - You're welcome.
我觉得我在写那本书的时候 就好像在造什么东西
I think that book that I wrote was like building something...
以免我忘记我们经历过点点滴滴
...so that I wouldn't forget the details of the time that we spent together.
你懂吗，就好像一个备忘录 告诉我我们的确见过面
You know, like, just as a reminder, that once, we really did meet.
你懂吗，那是真的，真的发生过
You know, that this was real, this happened.
我很高兴你这么说，因为...
I'm happy you're saying that, because...
我是说，我觉得自己很没用， 因为我从来不能这么洒脱
I mean, I always feel like a freak because I'm never able to move on like this:
人们只是随意留情， 甚至即使是认真的感情
People just have an affair, or even entire relationships...
...人们也会分手，然后忘记
...they break up and they forget.
就像换另一个牌子的麦片一样简单
They move on like they would have changed brand of cereals.
可我觉得我永远忘不了 跟我交往过的每一个人
I feel I was never able to forget anyone I've been with...
..因为他们每个人都有很不一样的特质
...because each person had their own specific qualities.
你不能取代任何人 失去的就失去了
You can never replace anyone. What is lost is lost.
每段感情结束的时候我都很受伤 我从来没有完全恢复过
Each relationship, when it ends, really damages me. I never fully recover.
所以我尽量避免介入感情
That's why I'm very careful with getting involved...
..因为那种痛真的是太深了！
...because it hurts too much.
即使是做爱！ 其实我不喜欢那样
Even getting laid, I actually don't do that...
因为我会很怀念一个人很平常的东西
...because I will miss of the person the most mundane things.
好比那些细节
Like I'm obsessed with little things.
或者也许我有点神经质 但当我小的时候...
Maybe I'm crazy, but when I was a little girl...
妈妈告诉我，我上学经常迟到
...my mom told me that I was always late to school.
有一天她跟着我想知道为什么
One day she followed me to see why.
我正看着栗子从树上掉下来，滚到便道上
I was looking at chestnuts falling from the trees, rolling on the sidewalk...
...或者是蚂蚁过马路，叶子在树干上的映出的倒影
...or ants crossing the road, the way a leaf casts a shadow on a tree trunk.
种种小事
Little things.
我想对人也是一样
I think it's the same with people.
我看到的是他们的细节，很细微
I see in them little details, so specific to each of them...
...那些能感动我的细节， 然后我就会想念他们，一直想念
...that move me and that I miss and will always miss.
你不能取代任何人
You can never replace anyone...
因为每个人都有他那种美丽的，独特的细微之处
...because everyone is made of such beautiful, specific details.
就好像我记得，你的胡子上有一点红色
Like, I remember the way your beard has a bit of red in it...
...我记得你离开的那天早上...
...and how the sun was making it glow...
...朝阳是怎样照的它闪闪亮
...that morning right before you left.
我一直记着，我非常怀念
I remembered that, and I missed it.
很神经质，对吧？
Really crazy, right?
现在我明白了，你想知道 为什么我写了那本烂书吗？
Now I know for sure. You wanna know why I wrote that stupid book?
- 为什么？ - 因为这样你就会参加巴黎的一场读者见面会
- Why? - So you'd come to a reading in Paris...
...而我就可以走过去，问你： “你到底去哪里了？”
...and I could walk up to you and ask, "Where the fuck were you?"
你真的觉得我今天会来？
No... You think I'd be here today?
真的，我之所以写这本书，从某种意义来讲 就是为了能找到你
I'm serious. I think I wrote it, in a way, to try to find you.
好啦，这....我知道这不是真的
Okay, that's... I know that's not true...
- 不过听了还是很高兴 - 我觉得这是真的
...but that's sweet of you. - I think it is true.
我们还有机会再见面吗？
What were the chances of us ever meeting again?
过了那个十二月，我想机率基本就是零了吧
After that December, I'd say almost zero.
不过反正我们也不是来真的，对吗？
But we're not real anyway, right?
我们只不过是那个老妇人梦中的角色
We're just characters in that old lady's dream.
她在她的病床上回忆年轻时的故事
She's on her deathbed, fantasizing about her youth.
所以我们当然会见面！
So of course we had to meet again.
天哪！你为什么那天没有出现在维也纳？
Oh, God. Why weren't you there in Vienna?
- 我告诉过你了！ - 我知道，但是...
- I told you why. - I know why, I just...
我真的希望你去了！
I wish you would have been.
我们的生活可能会完全不一样！
Our lives might have been so much different.
你真这么觉得？
You think so?
没错
I actually do.
也许不会呢，也许最后我们会憎恨对方呢
Maybe not. Maybe we would have hated each other eventually.
是吗，就像现在我们这样憎恨对方？
What, like we hate each other now?
你知道的，可能我们... 我们只适合那种偶遇...
You know, maybe we're... We're only good at brief encounters...
...在温暖的天气里 漫步在欧洲的街头
...walking around in European cities, in warm climate.
天哪，为什么我们没有交换电话号码呢？
Oh, God. Why didn't we exchange phone numbers and stuff?
为什么？
Why didn't we do that?
因为那时我们太年轻，不成熟？
Because we were young and stupid.
你觉得我们现在还是如此吗？
Do you think we still are?
我觉得，当你年轻的时候 你会相信...
I guess when you're young you just believe...
...你会认识很多人
...there'll be many people you'll connect with.
但后来你才会发现能交流的人其实很少
Later in life you realize it only happens a few times.
何况你又不能保证和他们好好相处 就这样，失去联系了
And you can screw it up, you know. Misconnect.
过去的就让它过去吧 事情本来就是这样的
The past is the past. It was meant to be that way.
你真的相信吗？ 任何事情都是注定的？
You really believe that? That everything's fated?
这个嘛，你明白吗，世界也许 没有我们想的那么多变
Well, you know, the world might be less free than we think.
是吗？
Yeah?
如果给定了特定的条件 就总会发生一样的结果
When given these exact circumstances, that's what will happen every time.
两份氢，一份氧，获得的总是水
Two part hydrogen, one part oxygen, you'll get water every time.
不， 我是说如果你祖母晚去世一个礼拜呢？
No, I mean, what if your grandmother had lived a week longer, you know?
或者是早一个礼拜去世？ 甚至是几天？
Or passed away a week earlier? Days, even?
事情都可能完全不一样！ 我坚信这一点！
Things might have been different.
- 不，你不能这样想，那只是... - 我知道对于大多数事情来说的确是注定的
- You can't think like that, it's... - You shouldn't on most things, but...
但是，只是这件事， 我觉得这事很不对劲
It's just, on this one, it seemed like something was off, you know.
你知道吗，在我结婚前的那个月 我一直都在想着你
In the months leading up to my wedding, I was thinking about you all the time.
即使在去婚礼的路上，我坐在车里 我的一个朋友送我进城
Even on my way there, I'm in the car, a buddy of mine is driving me downtown...
...我看着窗户 觉得我看到你了
...and I'm staring out the window and I think I see you...
...离教堂不远...
...not far from the church, right...
...收起一把雨伞，走进一家熟食店...
...folding up an umbrella and walking into a deli...
...就在百老汇和十三街的交汇处
...on the corner of 3th and Broadway.
那时我觉得我快要发疯了你知道吗？ 但现在我觉得这也许就是你
And I thought I was going crazy. But now I think it probably was you.
我住在百老汇和十一街的交汇处
I lived on th and Broadway.
你看！
You see?
那，结婚的感觉怎样，你还没说呢
So, what is it like to be married? You haven't talked much about that.
我没有吗？真奇怪
I haven't? How weird.
我不知道怎么说，我们是在上大学的时候认识的
I don't know. We met, you know, when I was in college.
有几年，我们分分合合，然后...
And we broke up and got back together for a period of years, and then...
怎么来着？我们好像又在一起了 然后她就怀孕了...
What? We were sort of back together and she was pregnant...
所以就结婚咯
...so marriage.
她怎么样？
What is she like?
她是个好老师，好妈妈
She's a great teacher, a good mom.
她很聪明，很漂亮
She's smart, pretty, you know.
我记得那时我想...
I remember thinking at the time...
...很多我所崇拜的人..
...that so many of the men that I admired most...
...他们的生命都奉献给了 比自己更重要的东西
...that their lives were dedicated to something greater than themselves.
所以你结婚是因为你崇拜的人都结婚了？
So you got married because men you admired were married?
不，不... 准确来说是... 我内心中有种对自我的完美期许
No, no. It's more like I had this... This idea of my best self, you know?
你懂吗？我想去追求那种自我
And I wanted to pursue that...
即使代价是失去真实的自我！
...even if it might have been overriding my honest self.
你懂我的意思吗？
You know what I'm saying?
我记得在那个时候 我并不觉得和“谁”结婚这个问题很重要
In the moment, I remember thinking it didn't much matter, the who of it all.
一个人并不是你生命的全部
I mean, that nobody is gonna be everything to you...
...到头来这只是一种负责的表现...
...and that it's just the action of committing yourself...
...就是说，负担起你的责任来，这才是最重要的
...you know, meeting your responsibilities, that matters.
我是说，爱是什么？ 如果它不是尊敬，信赖和钦佩的话？
I mean, what is love, right, if it's not respect, trust, admiration?
而我当时都感觉到了啊
And I... I felt all those things.
谈到现在，我感觉我好像在办一个托儿所
Cut to the present, and I feel like I'm running a nursery...
...跟一个我曾经约会过的人
...with somebody I used to date, you know.
我是说，我就像一个修道士
I mean, I'm like a monk, you know.
我在过去的4年中 做爱还不到10次
I mean, I've had sex less than 0 times in the last four years.
- 干嘛，干嘛？你笑我？ - 没有
- What, what? You laughing at me? - No.
- 听起来很可悲吗？ - 你看到过有修道士做过10次爱的吗？
- It sounds pathetic? - What monastery do monks have sex...?
好，你是对的，我比一般的修道士强，可以了吧？
Okay, you're right, I'm doing better than most monks.
但是我的确觉得，如果现在有人碰我的话
But I do, I feel like if somebody were to touch me...
我就会马上融化的了
...I would dissolve into molecules.
好啦，我们到了，该走了，快
Well, we're here. We've gotta go. Come on.
该死
Shit.
- （法语）晚上好 - （法语）晚上好
- 我很遗憾听到那些 - 什么？
- I'm sorry to hear that, you know. - What?
你对你的婚姻好像不怎么满意
You're not that happy with your marriage.
- 我刚才说到的那个朋友，她是神经科医生 - 她怎么了？
- This friend of mine, she's a shrink... - How's she doing?
她的生活很糟，不过...
She's a mess, but...
她告诉我她遇过很多夫妻...
No, she said she's been dealing with couples that are breaking up...
- 为了同样的理由而分开 - 什么理由？
...for the same reason. - What reason is that?
他们都期望，在共同生活了几年以后
They all expected, after a few years of living together...
...他们的热情，欲望还和当初一样
...for the passion, that desire, to be the same.
- 这是不可能的！ - 是啊，没错
- Yeah, right. - It's impossible.
而且谢天谢地...
And thank God...
...如果我们一直保持激情的话 我们会得动脉瘤的
...we'd end up with aneurysms in that constant state of excitement, right?
我们一生将一事无成
We'd do nothing at all with our lives.
如果你每5分钟就做一次爱 你还能写完你的书吗？
Would you have finished your book if you were fucking every five minutes?
我很乐意接受这个挑战
I might have welcomed the challenge, I mean...
但是，你懂吗，很自然的 当你太太生了小孩以后
It's natural for your wife after the birth of your son...
- 她就会把她的爱转移到小孩身上 - 当然
...to give all her love to the little one. - Of course.
想想看如果她执迷于性爱， 像野猫一样不停挑逗你
If she was obsessed with sex, riding you like a wildcat...
这不合情理，对吧？
That wouldn't make any sense, right?
不是这样的，你说得都很有道理 但这不是性的问题
Everything you're saying makes sense. It's not about sex.
是啊，我知道，很明显不是
No, I know. It's obvious.
我...
I...
你知道，现在的夫妻感情很复杂
You know, couples are so confused lately.
我觉得肯定是因为...
I think it must be that...
...男人总想让人觉得他们很重要 但事实已不是这样了
...men need to feel essential and they don't anymore.
多年以来，这种观念深植于他们脑海之中...
It's been imprinted in their head for so many years...
...好像他们就必须要是家里的顶梁柱
...that they had to be the provider.
比如，我在工作中就是一个坚强，独立的女性
Like, I'm a strong, independent woman in my professional life.
我不需要一个男人养我
I don't need a man to feed me...
...但我仍要一个男人爱我，而我也爱他
...but I still need a man to love me and that I could love.
- 好啦，我看到你的司机了 - 是的
- So your driver's here. - Yeah.
那，我想我该告别了
Well, I guess this is goodbye.
- 你最好把你的... - 不
- You better give me your... - No, no.
我们不如送你回家吧
Why don't we just give you a ride home?
- 这个嘛，我可以搭地铁，我没事 - 不，我...
- Well, I can take the M閠ro. I'm fine. - No, I...
我的飞机要10点才飞 我会提前两个钟头去
My flight's not until 0. I'll be arriving two hours early.
这样我们就可以继续谈了
This way we can keep talking.
- 先生，能...？ - 那不顺路的
- Monsieur, can...? - It's not on the way.
（法语）您能把我带到马场附近的十号路吗？
（法语）当然可以
- （法语）我们走吧 - （法语）麻烦您了
（法语）不，不，没问题
（法语）您就把我带到“水塔”地铁站附近就行了
- （法语）好吗？ - （法语）好的，没问题
（法语）谢谢
You told him where you are and all that?
你把你的住址什么的都告诉他了？
是的
Yeah.
- 他知道他要去哪了？ - 是的
- He knows where he's going? - Yes.
太好了
Glad somebody does.
- 这比搭地铁好，对吧？ - 当然
- But this is better than the M閠ro, right? - Definitely.
我在想，对我来说， 还是不要把事情想得太浪漫比较好
I was thinking, for me it's better I don't romanticize things as much anymore.
我一直都吃这个亏
I was suffering so much all the time.
我仍旧有很多梦想，但它们都与我的感情生活无关
I still have lots of dreams, but they're not in regard to my love life.
这样并不会让我不开心， 因为事情本来就是这样的
It doesn't make me sad, it's just the way it is.
这就是你为什么要和一个 不常见面的人发生感情吗？
Is that why you're in a relationship with somebody who's never around?
当然，我应付不了那种天天见面的感情
Yes, obviously I can't deal with the day-to-day life of a relationship.
我们相聚的时候可以充满激情
Yeah, we have this exciting time together...
...然后他离去了，我会很想他 不过我起码不会痛不欲生
...and he leaves and I miss him, but at least I'm not dying inside.
如果有人一直在我身边 我会觉得窒息！
When someone's always around me, I'm suffocating.
等等，可是你刚说你想要爱和被爱
No, wait, you just said that you need to love and be loved.
没错，但是当我的确这么做时， 这马上会让我恶心！
Yeah, but when I do, it quickly makes me nauseous.
真是个灾难
It's a disaster.
我是说，我只有一个人独处的 时候才会真正开心
I mean, I'm really happy only when I'm on my own.
即使是一个人，也比坐在 情人边上却心不在焉要来的好
Even being alone, it's better than sitting next to a lover and feeling lonely.
浪漫对我来说并不是一件容易的事
It's not so easy for me to be a romantic.
你开始的时候可能会这么做， 不过当你受过几次伤以后...
You start off that way, and after you've been screwed over a few times...
..你就会拒绝那些虚幻的想法 接受生活中的现实
...you forget about your delusional ideas and you take what comes into your life.
其实这也不见得对 我并没受过几次伤...
That's not even true. I haven't been screwed over...
...我只是有太多平庸的感情了
...I've just had too many blah relationships.
他们不是对我不好，他们都很关心我...
They weren't mean, they cared for me...
...但是我们却没有那种心灵上的沟通 或是发自心底的兴奋
...but there were no real connection or excitement.
起码我这边是这么感觉的
At least, not from my side.
天哪，真遗憾，有这么糟糕吗？
God, I'm sorry, is it really that bad?
没有吧，对吗？
It's not, right?
你知道吗，其实也不是这样的 我...
You know, it's not even that. I was...
我本来是好好的，直到我读到你那本该死的书
I was fine until I read your fucking book.
它把陈年往事又翻起来了，你知道吗？
It stirred shit up, you know?
它让我想起了，我曾经真正的浪漫过
It reminded me how genuinely romantic I was...
...我对于世界有过多少希望...
...how I had so much hope in things...
...而我现在已经完全不相信任何爱情了
...and now it's like I don't believe in anything that relates to love.
我已经感觉不到人之间的感情了
I don't feel things for people anymore.
从某种意义上来说，我所有的浪漫 都在一夜之间消耗光了...
In a way, I put all my romanticism into that one night...
...而我将永远不可能再有那种感觉了
...and I was never able to feel all this again.
就好像，那一夜不知道怎么 引发了我的全部感情...
Like, somehow this night took things away from me...
...而我把这些感情都向你倾诉出来 而你却把它们都从我身边带走了
...and I expressed them to you, and you took them with you.
这让我感到孤独！ 好像爱情再也不属于我一样！
It made me feel cold, like love wasn't for me.
我不相信，我不相信
I don't believe that. I don't believe that.
你知道吗？ 对我来说，现实和爱基本就是矛盾的
You know what? Reality and love are almost contradictory for me.
非常可笑，我每一个以前的男友 他们都结婚了
It's funny, every single of my exes, they're now married.
男人约我出去，然后我们分手 然后他们就结婚了.
Men go out with me, we break up, and then they get married.
之后之后他们打电话感谢我 教会了他们什么是爱
And later they call me to thank me for teaching them what love is...
...教会了他们去关心跟尊重女人！
...and that I taught them to care and respect women.
- 我想我也是那些男人中的一个 - 你知道吗，我真想杀了他们！
- I think I'm one of those. - I want to kill them!
他们为什么不向我求婚？ 我也许会拒绝，但至少他们也应该问我啊！
Why didn't they ask me? I would have said no, but they could have asked!
但我知道这是我的错 因为我总觉得他们不是我的如意郎君
I know it's my fault because I never felt it was the right man.
从来没有，但如意的人又是什么呢？ 你的真爱？
Never. But what does it mean, the right man, the love of your life?
这种想法简直可笑，说什么我们只有 找到了另一半人生才是完整的
The concept is absurd. We can only be complete with another person.
- 这太可恶了，不是吗？ - 我能说两句吗？
- It's evil, right? - Can I talk?
我想我是伤心过太多次了 然后又恢复了
I guess I've been heartbroken too many times and then I recovered.
于是现在，从一开始，我就不愿意付出努力
So now, you know, from the starts, I make no effort.
- 因为我知道一定不能成功 - 你不能这样
- I know it's not gonna work out. - You can't do that.
你不可以只是为了避免受伤害
You can't live trying to avoid pain...
- 就付出... - 好啦，我决定了
...at the expense... - Those are words.
我要离你远远的
I've gotta get away from you.
- 停车，我要下车！ - 不，别下车
- Stop the car, I wanna get out. - No, don't...
- 你知道在你身边... - 请继续讲...
- Keep talking. - It's being around you.
别碰我！你知道吗，我要叫辆计程车...
Don't touch me, you know. I want to get on a cab.
（法语）请停车，先生
（法语）过了红绿灯您就停，我去坐地铁
No, don't. No, no, keep going.
别，别停，继续开...
听我说，我真的很高兴... 谢谢你，请继续开...
Listen, I'm just so happy... Thank you, just keep going.
好啦
All right.
听我说，我真得很高兴 能跟你在一起
Look, I'm just so happy, all right, to be with you.
我真得很高兴你没有忘记我
I am. I'm so glad you didn't forget about me, okay?
是的，我没有，而这吓坏我了，知道吗？
No, I didn't. And it pisses me off, okay?
你到巴黎来，给我带来浪漫，但却结了婚
You come here to Paris, all romantic, and married.
去死吧你！
Okay? Screw you.
不要误会我，我并没有想要占有你
Don't get me wrong, I'm not trying to get you.
我只不过想把自己嫁出去
I mean, all I need is a married man.
这个问题很复杂 这甚至不仅仅是关于你
There's been so much water under the bridge, it's not even about you.
还有那段过去的时光， 那段永远不会再回来的时光！
It's about that moment in time that's forever gone.
你说了这么多，但你却根本不记得我们做过爱
You say that, but you didn't even remember having sex, so...
我当然记得
Of course I remembered.
- 你记得？ - 没错！
- You did? - Yes.
- 女人总喜欢这么掩饰自己 - 是吗？
- Women pretend things like that. - They do?
我应该说什么呢？ 说我记得公园里的红酒...
What was I supposed to say? That I remember the wine in the park...
...说我们我们一起看着星星落下太阳升起！
...and us looking up at the stars fading away as the sun came up?
我们做了两次爱，你这混蛋！
We had sex twice, you idiot!
好啦，你知道吗 我真得很高兴看到你
All right, you know what, I'm just happy to see you.
即使你已变得易怒和神经质
Even if you've become an angry, manic-depressive activist...
我还是很喜欢你 我还是愿意跟你待在一起！
...I still like you, I still enjoy being around you.
我也是，对不起，我不知道怎么了，我只是...
And I feel the same. I'm sorry. I don't know what happened, I just...
- 我需要发泄，我... - 没事
- I had to let it all out. - Don't worry about it.
我的感情生活太不顺利了
I'm so miserable in my love life, in my relationship.
所以我总是装作...好像我不在意它
I always act as... Like, you know, I'm detached.
但我真得痛不欲生 因为麻木而痛不欲生
But I'm dying inside. I'm dying because I'm so numb.
我不能感受到伤心和兴奋 我也不会感到苦涩，我只是...
I don't feel pain or excitement, I'm not even bitter, I'm just...
你以为只有你痛不欲生吗？
You think you're the one dying inside?
我的生活每时每刻全像是地狱
My life is 24/7 bad.
- 对不起... - 不要...
- I'm sorry. - No, no.
我唯一的快乐就是跟我儿子出去
I mean, the only happiness I get is when I'm out with my son.
我去找了婚姻咨询
I've been to marriage counseling...
我做了我从来没想过我会做的事
...I've done things I never thought I would have to do.
我点了蜡烛，买了自助读物，女性内衣...
I've lit candles, bought self-help books, lingerie.
- 蜡烛有用吗？ - 有个鬼用！
- Did the candles help? - Hell, no.
我没法用她想要的方式爱她
I don't love her the way she needs to be loved...
...我甚至根本看不到我们的未来 但当我看到我的小儿子
...and I don't even see a future for us, but then I look at my little boy...
...坐在桌子的对面 我就觉得我愿意承受一切折磨...
...sitting across from me, and I think I'd suffer any torture...
...只要能跟他一起度过 他生命中的每一刻
...to be with him for all the minutes of his life.
我一刻也不想缺
I don't want to miss out on one.
但是我的家里没有欢笑，没有快乐
But then, there's no joy or laughter in my home, you know?
- 我不希望他在这样的环境中长大 - 没有欢笑？那可太糟了
- I don't want him growing up in that. - No laughter? That's terrible.
我的父母在一起已经有35年了
My parents have been together 35 years...
而即使他们吵架之后，他们还会笑得一样开心
...and even when they fight they end up laughing.
我不想变成那种人 在52岁时离了婚...
I don't want to be one of those people who are getting divorced at 52...
...落着泪，承认从来就没有爱过自己的伴侣...
...and falling down into tears, admitting they never really loved their spouse...
...感觉自己的生活好像 完全被吸尘器吸走一样，一片空虚
...and they feel their life has been sucked up into a vacuum cleaner.
我也想拥有美好的生活 我也希望她拥有美好的生活
You know, I want a great life. I want her to have a great life...
这是她应得的！
...she deserves that.
但现在我们只是假装维系着婚姻，责任
But we're just living in the pretense of a marriage, responsibility...
...过着那种人们觉得你该过的日子
...you know, all these ideas of how people are supposed to live.
然后，我...我做了一个梦
But then I... I have these dreams...
什么梦？
What dreams?
我做了一个梦
I have these dreams, you know, that...
...梦见我站在月台上
...I'm standing on a platform...
...而你不停的坐火车经过
...and you keep going by on a train...
...你就是不停的经过，经过，经过
...and you go by, and you go by, and you go by, you go by.
然后我被吓醒，浑身冷汗
And I wake up with the fucking sweats.
然后我又做了一个梦...
And then I have this other dream...
...梦见你怀孕了，在床上躺在我身边，一丝不挂...
...where you're pregnant in bed beside me naked...
...而我非常非常想要抚摸你，但你跟我说不要， 然后你就把头别过去
...and I want so badly to touch you, but you tell me not to and you look away.
然后我... 我还是抚摸了你...
And I... And I touch you anyway...
...摸你的脚踝那里，你的皮肤是那样的柔软 使得我在哭泣中醒来
...right on your ankle, and your skin is so soft that I wake up in sobs, all right?
我的妻子就坐在那里，看着我 我却觉得她离我万里之遥
My wife is there looking at me, and I feel I'm a million miles from her.
我知道那不对劲，我...
And I know that there's something wrong, that I...
天啊！我不能再这样活下去了...
God, that I can't keep living like this...
...爱的意义一定不仅仅是责任
...that there's gotta be more to love than commitment.
但然后我又想 也许我已经不相信...
But then I think that I might have given up...
...浪漫的爱情了
...on the whole idea of romantic love.
我可能早已经不信了
That I might have put it to bed that...
自从那天我在那里没有见你
That day when you weren't there.
我想，我可能就开始消沉了
You know, I think I might have done that.
你为什么要和我说这些？
Why are you telling me all this?
对不起，我不知道 我...我应该...
I'm sorry. I don't know. I'm... I should...
我不应该说的
I shouldn't have.
你知道，太奇怪了
You know, it's so weird.
人们总是觉得自己是唯一痛苦的人
People think they are the only one going through tough times.
当我读那些文章的时候 我觉得你的生活是完美的
I mean, when I read the article, I thought your life was perfect.
有太太，孩子，出版了自己的作品
A wife, a kid, published author.
现在看来你的生活比我还糟！
But your personal life is more of a mess than mine.
对不起！
I'm sorry.
起码有些方面还过得去
Well, I'm glad it's good for something.
（法语）噢，先生，就是那儿！
（法语）把车停到那个通道里就行了
- 这里就是你住的地方？ - 没错
- This is where you live? - Yeah.
那现在看到看到我的生活比你还糟 觉得舒服点了吧？
So you're just relieved that I'm in even more deep shit than you are?
是的，你让我感觉好多了
Yes, you've made me feel better.
哦，那就好，我很高兴...
Oh, good, I'm glad.
不，我真的希望你的生活可以更好
No, I really wish you the best.
我不会因为自己无法有良好的感情 或是美好的家庭
It's not because I'm incapable of having a good relationship or a family...
就想要别人也跟我一样不开心
...that I wish everyone to be doomed like me.
我知道你总有一天会成为... 一个伟大的母亲的！
I'm sure you'd make... Be a great mom someday.
- 真的？你真的这么认为？ - 没错
- Really? You think so? - Yeah...
只要服一些抗忧郁药，你就行了！
...a few antidepressants, you know, you'll do great.
- 喊停！ - 停！
- Okay, say stop. - Stop.
- 好啦 - 准备好了吗？好啦
- Okay. - You ready? Okay.
- 我想试一下 - 什么？
- So I want to try something. - What?
我想看看你是会保持原样还是会融化
I want to see if you stay together or if you dissolve into molecules.
我融化了吗？
How am I doing?
保持原样！
Still here.
很好，我喜欢住在这儿
Good. I like being here.
这是你的公寓吗？
Is this your apartment?
不，我住在那里
No, I live down there.
- 那里？ - 是的
- Down there? - Yeah.
先生，我想送她进家门
Monsieur, I'm gonna walk her to her door.
（法语）他要送我进家门
太不可思议了！
This is incredible.
- 这就是你住的地方？ - 是的
- This is where you live? - Yeah.
- 你搬来这里多久了？ - 四年了
- How long have you been here? - Four years.
- 那告诉我.... - 什么？
- So tell me... - What?
你讲的那些你的梦，是真的吗？
Is it all true about your dreams...
还是只是为了骗我上床？
...or did you say that to hopefully get in my pants?
当然只是骗你上床啦！
I said that to get in your pants.
- 这是我的惯用伎俩 - 哦，有用吗？
- I use that all the time. - Oh, okay. Does it work?
恩，有时候
You know. Sometimes.
这是我的猫咪，哦，太可爱了 看看它
Here's my kitty. Oh, so cute. Look at him.
你知道我喜欢他的什么吗？
You know what I love about this cat?
每天早上我带他下来
Every morning I bring him to the courtyard...
...每一个早晨，他都会像是第一次来到这个院子一样！
...and every single morning he looks at everything like it was the first time.
每个角落，每棵树，每棵植物
Every corner, every tree, every plant.
都用他可爱的小鼻子去闻闻
Smells everything with his little cute nose.
我太喜欢他了！
Oh, I love my kitty. I love my kitty.
- 他叫什么？ - 奇
- What's his name? - Che.
奇？
Che?
- 怎么了？ - 听起来像共产党员
- What? - Commie.
不，“奇”在阿根廷是用来打招呼用的！
No, "che" in Argentina means "hey. "
- 真的？ - 是的
- Okay. - Yes.
哦，宝贝，哦，好啊，好啊
Oh, baby. Oh, yes, yes, yes.
我们晚上有个聚餐！超好玩的！
We're having a little party. It's so much fun.
（法语）你为晚餐准备了什么好东西？
（法语）塔布雷色拉
（法语）我过五分钟下来
（法语）你好
- So... - So.
（法语）这是谁？帅哥啊！
- （法语）他和我们共进晚餐吗？ - （法语）不，他要赶飞机
（法语）可惜他尝不到我的拿手菜了
（法语）他为什么不留下吃晚饭？
（法语）他不喜欢你的短裤！
（法语）我的短裤怎么了？
- 那.... - 那
你知道吗？我在想 你可以唱一首你的歌给我听吗？
You know what? I was thinking, would you play me one of your songs?
- 你会错过你的班机的！ - 不，不会的！
- You're gonna miss your flight. - I won't.
我坐在候机厅也只不过是读一个小时的报纸
I'm gonna be in the airport for over an hour, reading...
...所以还是听你唱一首歌给我听吧
...wishing you'd played me one of your songs.
一首？ 好吧，不过很短的
One song? Okay, but quickly.
好的
Okay.
我太喜欢这老楼梯了
God, I love these old staircases.
- 拿着！ - 什么，让我来？
- Hold this. - What, for me?
嘿，小家伙
Hey there, buddy.
奇
Che.
- 你想喝点茶吗？ - 好啊
- Would you like some tea? - Yeah, sure.
哇
Wow.
- 甘菊茶好吗？ - 恩，很好
- Is chamomile okay? - Yeah. Great.
- （法语）谢谢！ - 乱？（谐音）
- Merci. - Messy?
- 你觉得我的房间很乱？ - 不不不，我是说谢谢
- You think my apartment is messy? - No, no. Merci.
- （法语）非常感谢 - 哦，谢谢
- Merci beaucoup. - Ah, merci.
我想告诉你，你的法语进步很多
I meant to tell you, your French has improved a lot.
- 真的吗？ - 没错！
- Really? - Yeah.
你已经完全掌握这门语言了
Yeah, you've really mastered the language.
好吧，那你想要唱哪首歌？
All right, all right, what song are you gonna play me?
不行，我唱不了，这太丢人了
No, I can't. It's too embarrassing. It's been...
哇！不行！我这么费劲上来 就是为了这个，你不能这样坑我
Whoa. No way. No way. I came up here, you cannot crap out on me now.
就一首，随便那首都行
One song. Anything will be great.
但你会笑我的
But listen, you're gonna laugh at me.
- 你这么觉得？ - 是的！
- You think so? - Yes.
放心，我不会的
I doubt it.
好吧
Okay.
你想听什么？我有...
What do you want to hear? I have...
我有三首英文歌
I have three songs in English.
一首是唱我的猫的
One's about my cat...
...一首是唱我的前男友， 呃，前前男友...
...one's about my ex-boyfriend... Well, ex-ex-boyfriend...
...还有一首是....
...and there's one about...
是首华尔兹
Well, it's just a little waltz.
华尔兹？
A waltz? Yeah.
- 那就唱华尔兹吧 - 好吧
- Play the waltz. - Right.
我已经很久没弹吉他了，你确定你想听吗？
I haven't played it in a while. You sure?
当然
Okay.
好吧，华尔兹
All right, the waltz.
让我唱首华尔兹
Let me sing you a waltz
无从讲起，从我的心底
Out of nowhere, out of my thoughts
让我唱首华尔兹
Let me sing you a waltz
唱那次一夜缠绵
About this one-night stand
那晚，你是我的
You were, for me, that night
你是我生命中的全部梦想
Everything I always dreamt of in life
但你已经不在了
But now you're gone
你去了很远的地方
You are far-gone
你那的雨中小岛
All the way to your island of rain
对你来说，那只是一夜情
It was, for you, just a one-night thing
对我来说却远远不止
But you were much more to me
我想让你知道
Just so you know
我不管别人怎样说
I don't care what they say
我知道你对我的意义
I know what you meant For me that day
我只想再来一次
I just want another try
我只想再来一夜
I just want another night
即使这看起来毫无意义
Even if it doesn't seem quite right
但你对我来说
You meant, for me, much more
要比任何人都更重要
Than anyone I've met before
和你共度的一夜啊，小杰西
One single night with you, little Jesse
比得上和他人的一千个夜晚
Is worth a thousand with anybody
我没有痛苦，亲亲
I have no bitterness, my sweet
我永远不会忘记这一夜缠绵
I'll never forget this one-night thing
即使明天我在他人怀中
Even tomorrow, in other arms
我的心还会随你而去，直到生命尽头
My heart will stay yours until I die
让我唱一首华尔兹
Let me sing you a waltz
无从讲起，从我的心底
Out of nowhere, out of my blues
让我唱一首华尔兹
Let me sing you a waltz
唱那可爱的一夜情
About this lovely one-night stand
- 不要停，再来一首，求你了 - 不行，说好了的！
- No, one more! Please, please. - No! It was our deal.
一首，就一首，别，别
One... One song. No, no, no.
你可以喝完你的茶再...
You can have your tea and then...
- 好吧，我问你个问题 - 什么？
- All right, let me ask you one question. - What?
你是不是每次不管谁来 就在歌词里换个名字？
Do you just plug that name in for every guy that comes up here?
当然了
Yes, of course.
你以为呢？我是写给你的？你疯了吗？
What do you think, that I wrote the song about you? Are you nuts?
这是你吗？小对眼塞琳？
Is this you? Little cross-eyed Celine?
- 是的，那张很好笑 - 可爱
- Yes. That's funny. - Cute.
- 这就是你的祖母？ - 是的
- Is that your grandmother? - Yeah.
哇
Oh, wow.
- 你要加点蜂蜜吗？ - 好的
- You want some honey? - Yeah, sure.
你听过尼娜·西蒙的演唱会吗？
Did you ever see Nina Simone in concert?
没有，不敢相信她已经不在了
No, I never did. I can't believe she's gone.
我知道，太让人伤心了
I know, it's so sad.
谢谢
Thanks.
真热
It's hot.
我听过她两次演唱会
I saw her twice in concert.
她真棒！
She was so great.
这是她的歌里我最喜欢的几首之一
That's one of my favorite songs of hers.
她太棒了！
She was so great.
她在演唱会里太有趣了
She was so funny in concert too.
她会...她会在一首歌唱到一半时的时候
She would... She would be right in the middle of a song and then...
...你知道吗，停下来...
...you know, stop...
...从钢琴边起身，一直走到舞台边上
...and walk from the piano all the way to the edge of the stage.
像这样，非常慢的
Like, really slowly.
然后她开始对观众中的某人说话
And she'd start talking to someone in the audience.
哦，耶，哦，耶
"Oh, yeah, baby. Oh, yeah.
我也爱你
I love you too. "
然后她又走回去，不急不忙的，
And then she'd walk back. Take her time, no hurry, you know.
她的大屁股真可爱
She had that big, cute ass.
她就这么慢慢挪着
She would move.
然后就走回钢琴旁再唱一段
And then she would go back to the piano and play some more, you know.
然后她会，我也不知道...
And then she would, I don't know...
...一首歌唱了一半又唱另外一首
...just start another song in the middle of another.
你懂吗，好像，又停下，然后这样
You know, like, stop again, and be like:
那边那位，你能挪挪那电扇吗
"You over there, can you move that fan.
你真可爱
You're cute.
哦，耶
Oh, yeah. "
宝贝，你会错过你的班机的
Baby, you are gonna miss that plane.
我知道
I know.